<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration, of the reasons, moveing Don Emanuel, borne Prince of Portugall Haveing been heretofore a devotary, under the name of Pater Felix, in the Order of the Barefooted Carmelites, to forsake the Romish religion, to joyne himself unto the catholick &amp; apostolick Church; and in the same to professe the purity of the Gospell. The abridgement of this declaration was presented vnto the Consistory of the French Church at Delf signed with the hand of the said Prince, and after sermon read in his name to all the assembly, and after all, ratifyed by his owne mouth, the 15. day of Ianuary 1634. With certaine letters written from Brussels, since his coming over into these provinces. Translated out of French into English by I.R.M.D.</title>
            <author>Manuel, Prince of Portugal, 1600-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21332</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855386</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855386</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21332)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1235:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration, of the reasons, moveing Don Emanuel, borne Prince of Portugall Haveing been heretofore a devotary, under the name of Pater Felix, in the Order of the Barefooted Carmelites, to forsake the Romish religion, to joyne himself unto the catholick &amp; apostolick Church; and in the same to professe the purity of the Gospell. The abridgement of this declaration was presented vnto the Consistory of the French Church at Delf signed with the hand of the said Prince, and after sermon read in his name to all the assembly, and after all, ratifyed by his owne mouth, the 15. day of Ianuary 1634. With certaine letters written from Brussels, since his coming over into these provinces. Translated out of French into English by I.R.M.D.</title>
                  <author>Manuel, Prince of Portugal, 1600-1666.</author>
                  <author>I. R. M. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Successors of G. Thorp],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Durham University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20876:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20876:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DECLARATION, Of the reaſons, moveing</hi> DON EMANVEL<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Borne Prince of Portugall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Haveing been heretofore a Devotary, under the name of <hi>Pater Felix,</hi> in the Order of the Barefooted Carmelites, to forſake the Romiſh Religion, to joyne himſelf unto the Catholick &amp; Apoſtolick Church; and in the ſame to profeſſe the purity of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Abridgement of this Declaration was preſented vnto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory of the French Church at Delf ſigned with the hand of the ſaid Prince, and after Sermon read in his name to all the Aſſembly, and after all, ratifyed by his owne mouth, the 15. day of Ianuary 1634.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With certaine Letters written from Bruſſels, ſince his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming over into theſe Provinces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the French into Engliſh by</hi> I. R. M. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Ezech. 20.18, 19.</bibl>
               <p>Walke ye not in the ſtatutes of your Fathers, neither obſerve their judgments, nor defile your ſelvs with their Idols. I am the Lord your God, walke in my Statutes, and keep my judgments, and doe them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1634.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20876:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20876:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> DECLARATION, Of the reaſons, moveing DON EMANVEL, <hi>Borne Prince of Portugall,</hi> Haveing been heretofore a Devotary of the order of the unſhod Carmelites, under the name of <hi>Pater Felix,</hi> to depart from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, for to adjoyne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto the <hi>Reformed</hi> church, of the <hi>Vnited Provinces,</hi> and to profeſſe in the ſame <hi>the Purity of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Bove all things, I thanke the Lord, that the citty which did embrace me, come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the world, and the Church wherein I receaved the H. Baptiſme, ſhall heare this day the publick witneſſe, that I am to give of my faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20876:3"/>Thoſe, from whome not long ſince I am departed, and thoſe, amongſt whome I now ranck my ſelf, (though different of judgment, in matter of ſalvation) ſeem notwithſtanding (as I conceave) to have a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon deſire, to know the motives of my change in Religion.</p>
            <p>Therefore not to fruſtrate the one or other of their deſire, and to obey the Counſell of the Apoſtle Peter, to <hi>be allwayes ready,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>to give an anſwer to every man, that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſse and reverence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I teſtify, I have not conſulted with fleſh or blood, but with the Spirit of the Lord; which often hath forced mee, to follow his precepts, ſpeaking of Babylon:<note place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> 
               <hi>Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, and that ye receave not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not, but there wilbe many amongſt the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes of the Religion, which I now embrace, that will abandon me, the one will ſoile mee with falſe backbiteings, the other will ſeeke to devoure me with ſeverall calumniations, others will accuſe me of teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, others againe will take up ſome perverſe opinion againſt me.</p>
            <p>All this have I propounded unto my ſelfe; and ſeeing thoſe, which be true Chriſtians, ought not to refuſe, to beare a little weight of the Croſſe of Ieſus Chriſt after him, I will comfort me with that he ſayth to thoſe which ſhall be ſlandred for his holy names ſake: <hi>Bleſſed are they,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.10 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>which are perſecuted for righteouſneſse ſake, when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evill againſt you falſly, for my ſake; Rejoyce and be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20876:3"/>
exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doe no wiſe regard the reproaches but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce the more that I receave them for this cauſe, and forgive unto all that utter theſe things againſt me: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing unto my ſelfe, for a law of patience, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>who being curſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3, 44.</note> 
               <hi>did not curſe againe;</hi> and his commaund, <hi>that we ſhould bleſſe them that curſe us, doe good to them that hate us, and pray for them, which deſpitefully vſe us, and perſecute us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, I doe not onely neglect all tongues and pennes, that for this cauſe might be injurious unto me, but rather will pray to God for them, as Steven did: <hi>Lord impute not this ſinne vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire every one might take notice, that my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting out of my Monaſtery, where I made my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, was neither ſecret nor fugitive, but publicke &amp; with knowledge of the place I was to travell too; with notice and full conſent of the Superiour of that order, in which I was, as appeares by the letter of Obedience, graunted unto mee, which remaines in the handes of a Devotarie of the ſame order, which I tooke with me for company. I have not donne it privately, for the Sereniſſima Infante, on whome I hope God had mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, both knew it, and allowd of it; and I alſo certifyed it unto my Lord the Prince of Portugall, my moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lord and Father, who did alſo approve of it.</p>
            <p>One thing I confeſſe, that I did not detect unto them my purpoſe, takeing a pretext to come into theſe Countryes, without which I could never
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20876:4"/>
have hoped to enjoy this liberty.</p>
            <p>As concerning my life and converſation in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery, it were not fitting, that I ſhould prayſe my ſelf; but for defence againſt the malitious detractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which they thinke to caſt upon me, as if I were departed for ſome Crime committed, or that the rigour of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der did ſtomack me to ſtay there; I referre my ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the teſtimony, which may eaſily be gathered partly by the Letter of Obedience, which is not graunted, but with approbation of being free from the bonds of Cenſure: as alſo by thoſe Letters, which I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaved, whilſt I have been in this Country, from the Sereniſſima Infante, from my Lord the Prince of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall, my Father, from the Provinciall of my order, and from ſome eminent perſons: of which ſome of them remained in the hands of him, that was my aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in my journy, who is returned to the monaſtery, and ſome ſhall be joyned behind this declaration; all as witneſſes of a good affection towards me. And ſince a yeare, or there about, that I came over hither, hath there beene none that hath brought any accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; yea have not entertained a bad report of me, ſave ſince they ſaw me frequent the Sermons in the Reformed Church; but the knowledge they have of my life, and converſation, and their owne conſcience, will make them lye to God, and to the world, in all things they ſhall oblaterate againſt me. The long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is a ſufficient teſtimony of my good reſpect and honour, in which I lived amongſt them; And I aſſure them, that I will not recompenſe evill for evill, though
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20876:4"/>
I were provoked thereunto: neither ſhall I touch the honour of any perſon, or the order which I have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed.</p>
            <p>Eſteeming it a thinge more honourable, to diſpiſe the ſayings of the imprudent, then to reſiſt them.<note place="margin">Prov. 26.4</note> 
               <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer not a foole, according to his folly, least thou be alſo like unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they object, that worldly conſiderations have moved me to depart, I confeſſe ſome have; but they ſerved my intention no further, but as meanes to the principall; which was ſpirituall, and for my ſoule; for the which, by the freedom of my body, I have ſought to attayne to the liberty of the pure worſhip of God; and for my mouth, that I might without daunger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the holy name of God, and declare his truth; of which I had at that time ſufficient knowledge to urge me to remove: but ſince the one and the other were ſo neare combined, that I could not ſever them; I was conſtrained to employ them both by one &amp; the ſame meanes.</p>
            <p>It was not to take unto my ſelfe a larger freedome for the delights of this world, for there is not ſo ſmal a Chappell, ſo well barred and ſhutt up by the moſt rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous monaſteriall ſtatutes and inſtitutions, but there may be found one rift or other, by which any thinge may ſlide in, that will ſerve ſuch as have with their mouth onely denyed their luſts.</p>
            <p>Neither was it on hope or exſpectation of any worldly inheritance: for whence ſhould ſuch things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall me? It is knowne to every one, to what caſe the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20876:5"/>
Royall Blouds of Portugall is driven, by the unjuſt poſſeſſion of the howſe of Spaine, who not being contented to have robbed from it, his Royall and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimoniall goods; hath alſo forced the perſon of Don Emanuel, my honourable Lord and Father, to deſiſt from all rights and titles thereunto; in ſo much, that at the Court in Bruſſells, they will not afford him the title of a Prince.</p>
            <p>That every one then may rightly underſtand from the beginning the meanes of this my converſion, whereof I give the Lord alone glory, I would give the whole world to underſtand, that Don Emanuell, Prince of Portugall, my honourable Lord and Father, hath allwayes, and doth yet for the preſent, make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Romiſh Religion, and that my Lady <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia of Naſſau,</hi> my honourable Lady and Mother (whom God hath taken into his Kingdome) hath allwayes profeſſed the Catholick and Apoſtolick Religion, in the Chriſtian Reformed Church; as alſo ſhe departed in that ſayd fayth. The difference of Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them was the cauſe (for each of them were ſtrongly addicted to their Religion) that there was a deviſion of their Children, concerning matters of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: yet have I had that benefit, together with my Brother Don William, and my beloved Siſters, that we receaved the H. Baptiſme in the Reformed Church of this towne, and there was promiſed by thoſe that did preſent me to the Baptiſme, that I ſhould be inſtructed as much (as lay in them) in the truth of this Religion: And my Lady, my Mother, findeing herſelf principally
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20876:5"/>
and moſt ſtrictly to be obliged by this bond, hath not beene defective in her duety, to fulfill her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, whereas children in their tender yeares, commonly are left under the tuition of their mother, till the ſtrength of their body, and the capacity of their underſtanding, might be more capable to ſoare up high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; I did remain under the protection and wardſhip of my Lady, my mother, of happy memory, till the age of 12 years old, during which time, ſhe did inſtruct me in the principles of the knowledg of my ſalvation; have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taught me the articles of the Creed, the Lords prayer, and the ten Commandements, with a ſmall Catechiſme. And God, through his grace, hath ſo bleſſed theſe principles and impreſſions in me, that ſince that time, I have beene allwayes much addicted unto this Religion, which my Lord the Prince my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, obſerveing by my converſation and manners, did take it ſo heavily, that ſeeing me one day, haveing the New Teſtament by me, tooke it from me, and caſt it into the Garden, did entertaine me hardly with ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and blowes, whereupon my Lady my Mother, of happy memorie, to comfort me, tould me, I was happy to ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake. Then my Lord the Prince my Father, to prevent that which he did all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpye, ſent me and my Brother into Fraunce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending us to Don Chriſtofer, Prince of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, our honourable Vncle, who alſo maketh a full profeſſion of the Romiſh Religion, that the firſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions we had receaved, might be reprinted, by new
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20876:6"/>
inſtructions, our underſtandings being of ſmall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ready to receave any thing. But God, who had from my youth wrought ſo much good upon me, did grant me to record that which I had learnd; which kept me allwayes in a continuall doubt, that that which they taught me concerning Gods ſervice in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, was not the true ſervice of God. In the meane while, I lived in that Errour, in the time of my abideing there, following my inſtructions, which my Lord the Prince my father had cauſed to be taught unto me: And confeſſe, though my publick profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the doubtfull ſuſpicion which I had of doing well, (following the broad way of the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,) had cauſed me to take his ſide; nevertheleſſe I felt certaine inclinations, makeing me averſe from it, and a deſire to know the way to ſalvation in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Religion, of which my honourable Father &amp; Mother made profeſſion, each of them glorying of the true Chriſtianity, which haveing but one truth for a foundation, could not ſuffer ſuch a contradiction.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſſe of my deſire could not be accompliſhed ſo ſoone as I had wiſhed; the Authority of my Lord my Father, the manner of life in the world, in reſpect of my birth, the exerciſes and ſeverall ſervices, in which they have employed me, and the naturall negligence of man, which makes him ſo careleſſe of his ſalvation, eſpecially in his nonage, had by the multitude of aſhes ſo covered the ſparkes of fire, that they were allmoſt wholy ſmoothered, &amp; did appeare no ſooner then that good God, (who quencheth not the ſmoaking flaxe)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20876:6"/>
by the holy ſtirring of his Spirit, hath revived and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated that ſparke at that time; when there was leaſt appearance for my ſalvation, and I lay deepeſt grove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the greateſt darkneſſe of a devout ſuperſtition; and in an Order, into which, the adviſe of ſeverall men, with many conſiderations of the State, in which <hi>I</hi> found my ſelfe to be, did enduce me to tread; hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to finde there a ſhorter &amp; a clearer way then is the common roade, departing out of this world, that ſo with leſſe trouble, as I thought I might com into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. I made my promiſe, and receaved my Veſture from the hands of the Sereniſſima Infante: therein <hi>I</hi> lived about 4 yeare and a halfe, and findeing my ſelfe free from all worldly care, haveing delivered into the hands of her Highneſſe my place of a Captaine of a Company of Souldiers, with which they had furniſhed me, I did beſtow the ſolitarines of my profeſſion, and the time which I had, on the learning of the Lattin tongue, and of Philoſophy; haveing made a good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into them, they did ſerve me for a help, to get by reading of ſeverall bookes the beſt ſcience, which is the true knowledge of God, to his honour, my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and edification of others, propounding unto my ſelfe for a marke, to eſtabliſh my ſelfe in the fayth of the Romiſh Religion, in which I lived as in my proper Element.</p>
            <p>But the Almighty God, who had allready decreed me to goe out of the Kingdome of darkneſſe, unto the clearneſſe of his light, and from the publick doctrine of lyes, unto his truth, hath changed that pernicious
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20876:7"/>
juyce, of which my veines were ful, into a ſaving nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of my ſoule; and the weapons with which I had thought to help my ſelf, to reſiſt thoſe that ſhould reſiſt me in my religion, are become ennemyes to my purpoſe, and forcible meanes, to conquer me, and to draw me to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For, according to the cuſtome, uſed in the Romiſh Religion, and in the Monaſteryes, thinking my ſpeciall ſtudy ſhould conſiſt, in reading of the moſt renowned Doctors, whom they condigne with the honourable title of Fathers, I did employ my ſelf unto that; but meeting with ſeverall difficultyes, yea contrarietyes, in one and others opinion, yea that the moſt famous amongſt them, and whom they alledge moſt for their advantage, (viz. S. Auguſtin) hath written a whole book of recalling of that which he had formerly falſely beleeved and taught, I beganne to ſuſpect their write<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to dive well into the truth of this thinge; without bindeing my ſelfe ſuperſtitiouſly unto the title of Fathers; I concluded with my ſelfe, that thoſe Fathers heretofore were but Children, and that their light was derived from elſe where. I therefore traced their diſcent, not of their perſons, but of their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; whoſe originall I found muſt have beene in the holy Scriptures of the Prophets and Apoſtles, who are the firſt Fathers, on whoſe foundation the Church of God is grounded; whoſe Cornerſtone is Chriſt; and that Chriſt is the true light, inlightening the whole world; from the gliſtering beames of that ſtone have they derived all the light they had, as Iohn ſayth:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20876:7"/>
               <hi>Search the Scriptures;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 5.39 2 Pet. 1.19</note> And Peter compares it to a <hi>light ſhineing in darknes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being then come to the ſource and ſpring of life, my ſpirit did ſuggeſt unto me, that I ought not to dive furder, and that by the pureneſſe thereof I ought to judge of the taſte, colour, and clearneſſe of the flowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waters, which commonly participate with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes, occurring in the veines of the Earth. The ſame can be manifeſted by paralelling of a great number of writeings of theſe good Fathers, with the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in which, remarkable tokens of their errour may be ſpied, and that they have not allwayes rightly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the way of truth: But as their writeings can not totally be rejected, ſince they are not throughout corrupted, ſo alſo may they not fully be receaved, as an infallible rule of Fayth. I ſort them amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and publick Teachers of the truth, not as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of it; for Gods truth needeth not the teſtimony of man.</p>
            <p>It is not my purpoſe, nor my profeſſion, to play the Artiſt, but to manifeſt whoſe Diſciple I am; but that the Fathers (amongſt the reſt S. Auguſtin and S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, deſireing that their writeings ſhould be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the holy Scripture) have ſhewed me this; and I alſo purpoſe to hould my ſelfe to this rule. In it I have read the prohibition God made, concerning the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices contrary to his commaunds, and againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion the Iſraelites made of the inſtitution of their Fathers. <hi>Walke ye not in the Statutes of your Fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 20, 18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerve their judgements. I am the Lord your God,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20876:8"/>
walke in my Statutes, and keep my judgements, and doe them.</hi> In the Goſpell I read: <hi>One is your Maſter even Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23, 8.</note> Whence I conclude, that the writeings of the Doctors muſt be examined by the word of God; and if they teach otherwiſe, they are ſeducers.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I finde written, <hi>that the Sheepe of Chriſt heare his voice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 10, 27</note> and follow no ſtrangers, but fly from them. Whence I conclude, that, whoſoever ſpeaketh other language then doth Chriſt unto his flock, (which is his Church,) are no true Sheepheards, but deceavers. I read alſo the prayſe Paul gives the holy Scripture; which was then receaved in the Church of God (as he ſayth:) <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, &amp; is profitable for Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>for reproofe, for correction, for instruction in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, thorowly furniſhed vnto all good workes;</hi> whereby <hi>I</hi> conclude, ſeeing by the ſame a Chriſtian, who is a man of God, may be perfect and throughly furniſhed to all good workes; that it is not onely convenient, but alſo ſufficient unto ſalvation. They ſlaunder therefore vilely, that condemne that Spirit of God of imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who did inſpire it unto his Servants, Prophets, Evangeliſts, &amp; Apoſtles; as the Teachers of the Romiſh Church doe. And ſeeing it is called by the Prophet David,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105.</note> 
               <hi>A lampe to his feet, and a light to his pathes;</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is not darke, and that it needs no ſtrange light to make it ſelfe knowne: It being ſo then, that the Goſpell of Chriſt is the onely rule of our Fayth, like as the Law of God is the onely rule of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, who ſhall hinder me from ſubſcribeing and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20876:8"/>
ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to the words of the Apoſtle, relateing twice; And denouncing <hi>a Curſe against himſelf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Angell of Heaven, if he taught other doctrine then he had taught afore;</hi> and to eſteeme all doctrine of man accurſed, whether by tradition, or the unwritten word, whereof the foundation may not be found, in the written words of the Prophets, Evangeliſts, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, that is, in the writeings of the New and Ould Teſtament, which we, and they of the Romiſh Church confeſſe to be Canonicall.</p>
            <p>Therefore they of the Romiſh Religion, to ſupply the imperfections, wherewith they ſlaunder the holy Scripture, obtrude the writeings of ſuch perſons, which were not inſpired immediately by the ſpirit of the Lord, affirming, <hi>that the holy Scripture of it ſelfe is not authentick, without the authority of the Church, and the Church is ancienter then the Scripture,</hi> (a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thinge, for whence did the Church learne, but from the Scripture,<note place="margin">Eck. loc. commnn. cap. 3.</note> and the Diſciple but from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?) <hi>as alſo that the Scripture is like to a leaden rule, like a noſe of wax, which they can turne and bend which way they list as a Fable of Æſop, without the authority of the Church, that it is a cauſe of hereſies, and therefore prohibited to be read by laymen.</hi> And the Councell of Trent, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the unwritten traditions to the ſame honour and dignity, with the holy Scriptures, as being the ſame, the foundation of Fayth, without which foundation the authority and dignity of the Scripture falls to the ground; in truth, being inſolent, blaſpheming, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing the dignity of Gods word, and makeing the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20876:9"/>
ſame depend upon human authority; Me thinks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for this conſideration onely, I have cauſe enough to deteſt all ſuch Religion, which is in a high degree, injurious to God; and in which perſiſting, there is no ſalvation: For though they vaunt in words, of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, yet in truth, they performe more unto the Creature then unto the Creatour, and the honour of man is more advanced there, then the honour of God.</p>
            <p>That Religion vindicateth unto her ſelfe (though by unjuſt uſurpation) the honourable tittle to be the Church of Chriſt, but ſhe wants the eſſentiall ſignes thereof, which are the ſincere preaching of his holy Word, and the lawfull adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Concerning the word of God, the common people knowe it not, no body may read it without permiſſion of their Superiour, and if the Preachers read the ſame unto the people, whether in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell or Epiſtles, or in the adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or whether a part of it be graunted unto them in their bookes of devotion, as in the Mattins and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Lady Mary, or other Saints, it is all wayes in a language unknowne to the people, yea oftentimes paſſing the underſtanding of him that teacheth it; Whence it comes that that great Apoſtle of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.11.</note> teacheth concerning unknowne languages in the Church, <hi>that he that heareth, not knoweing the power of the voice, ſhall be vnto him that ſpeaketh a Barbarian; and he that ſpeaketh ſhall be a Barbarian vnto him.</hi> That prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of reading the word of God, is the cauſe of ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20876:9"/>
many errours in the Romiſh Church; and one may apply juſtly unto the ignorant, that which Chriſt ſayth unto the Sadduces,<note place="margin">Mat. 22, 29</note> 
               <hi>you erre not knoweing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the interpretations they give of it, and for the applications, they are either falſe or ridiculous; few of them true, which may be gathered by theſe ſmall rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, without touching the whole pieces, from the beginning to the end, as may be ſeene in the whole booke of conformityes, of the pretended S Francis, printed at Bullin, dedicated unto the Cardinall du Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veve, 1590, a booke full of Fables, falſe miracles, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious lyes, and horrible blaſphemies, yea ſuch a booke, that words are not ſufficient to expreſſe the inpudency thereof: by this Example onely, the reſt may be judged. In the ſecond preface fol. 6. pag. 2. colum. 1: of the ſaid conformityes, the Author ſhewes, that S. Francis was a man extraordinarily ordayned by the providence of God, to be ſent into the world, and, to ſhew that, he alleages that of the firſt of Geneſ. <hi>Let us make man,</hi> which words (ſayth the Author of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formityes, is <hi>of the whole Trinity, ſending S. Francis into the world;</hi> Therefore not of Adam; for there were not two men created, but one; but it is apparent by the text, that it was Adam; therefore not S. Francis: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould the foundation of his Holineſſe lyeth in lyes, and all the reſt of the Types of the Ould Teſtament, and all the perſons that ſhould have beene figures of him, are founded on the ſame truth. This booke was brought hither amongſt theſe, which were taken in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20876:10"/>
the Silver-fleet, by the Admirall Pieter Heynen, Anno 1628, and may be ſeen at Delft. In the ſame page, to ſhew how great the renowne of his power ſhould be, Chriſt is brought in ſpeaking to S. Francis:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.9</note> 
               <hi>I have made thee a great name, like vnto the name of the great men, that are in the Earth:</hi> Words which Nathan the Prophet, by the commaund of God, ſpoke to David; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after, the Author addeth: <hi>His name is become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecl. 45.4.5</note> (the reaſon?) <hi>for he hath made him honourable amongſt Kings, and hath ſhewed him his glory, he ſanctified him in his faythfulneſſe and meekneſſe:</hi> Words that are ſpoken of Moſes the great Leader of the people of God. They are not aſhamed thus to ſport themſelves with the Scripture. Of the ſame brood is that that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, a certaine writer reprehending thoſe which ſpent the revenues of Biſhopricks and other benefices, to keepe Whores, Comedians, and Hounds, allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the words, which our Saviour ſpeaketh to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Canaan, who prayed for the deliverance of her child:<note place="margin">Marc. 7.27</note> 
               <hi>It is not meet to take the childrens bread, and to cast it vnto Doggs;</hi> and to threaten thoſe that did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre Eccleſiaſticall benefices upon thoſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity, or others allied unto them; <hi>Wo vnto him that buildeth the citty in blood;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2, 12</note> and when amongſt the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the coronation of the Pope, after that by the Canonicall men of S. Iohn of Lateran, he is ſett into a cloſe-ſtoole, the Cardinalls lifteing of him up, with great ſtate, doe they not mock at the word of God, when they utter the words of the ſong of Hannah, the mother of the Prophet Samuel: <hi>He rayſeth up the poore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20876:10"/>
out of the duſt, and lifteth vp the beggar from the dunghill, to ſet them amongſt Princes, &amp;c.</hi> And after,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2, 8</note> that the ſaid Pope is thus raiſed, he taketh a handfull of ſmall mony, like to farthings, called <hi>Bajoci,</hi> (takeing heed there be neither gould nor ſilver amongſt it, for feare of lyeing,) and caſteth that amongſt the people, ſaying that which S. Peter ſaid unto the poore lame man, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for almes deeds: <hi>Silver or gould have I not, but that which I have I give vnto you.</hi> Is he not prophane and lye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? for his Officers, to make for him a free paſſage, caſt a heap of mony along the ſtreets, in token of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, for to get the people out of his way: Theſe are but glimpſe of their prophane applications.</p>
            <p>As for the falſe interpretation of the holy Scripture, one may meet with them ſo frequently in the vulgar tranſlation of the Bible, which the Counſell of Trente hath Canonized, and would have to be of greater au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then the Originall Hebrew or Greek, that it ſeemeth that the intention of the ſaid Counſell was, to obtrude a baſtard in ſtead of a legitimate; that is a falſe doctrine in ſtead of a true one. Theſe few Examples ſhall ſuffiſe: It is ſaid in Geneſis, that <hi>the ſeed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall breake the head of the Serpent;</hi> that ſeed of the woman is Chriſt, which is of the ſeed of the woman, not of the ſeed of the man, like as the Lady Mary, and the verſion of the Romiſh Religion, to attribute that unto the virgin Mary, which belonges onely to Chriſt, hath tranſlated it in this manner, that <hi>the bruiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the head of the Serpent</hi> ſhould be attributed unto the woman, not unto her ſeed; thoſe which have but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20876:11"/>
ſmall inſight into the Hebrew tongue, muſt without contradiction confeſſe, that this is falſely tranſlated; For the article in the Originall Hebrew, hath a refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto the word <hi>Seed,</hi> not to the word <hi>Woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.1.</note> In Eccleſiaſtes, the Hebrew Text ſayth: <hi>No man knoweth either love or hatred, by all that is before him;</hi> the Roman verſion hath it, <hi>a man knoweth not whether he be worthy of love or hatred,</hi> and that to eſtabliſh the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and incertainty of mans ſalvation; they have moſt wickedly joyned unto it, <hi>but all things are kept in vncertainty for time to come.</hi> In Pſalm 94. <hi>Worſhip at his footſtoole,</hi> the Roman verſion is, <hi>worſhip his footstoole;</hi> To draw from them the adoration of the Creatures. In the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, <hi>Iacob worſhipped</hi> (viz. God) <hi>upon the toppe of his ſtaffe,</hi> the Roman verſion hath it, <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the toppe of his ſtaffe.</hi> It may be he had thereon, ſome image of the virgin Mary, which came not into the world, but many ages after him. In the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, chapt. 13: <hi>Forget not to doe goood, or to communicate, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is wel pleaſed;</hi> the Roman ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>for God is appeaſed by ſuch ſacrifices,</hi> and that to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, the merites of good workes.</p>
            <p>And to prove that there are two ſwords in the Church, the one ſpirituall, and the other materiall, Boniface the eight Pope of that name, abuſed that, which the Diſciples ſpoke unto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Extr. vog. com. tit. 8 Voam Sanct.</note> 
               <hi>Behould two ſwords;</hi> upon which Chriſt ſhould have anſwered, <hi>'t Is enough.</hi> And to prove, that the employeing of this ſword appertaineth unto the Pope, as being the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour of Peter, are not theſe words applyed to good
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20876:11"/>
purpoſe: <hi>Put thy ſword into thy ſheath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Pope Innocent the third, for to extoll the Popes authority above the Emperours; writeing unto the Emperour of Conſtantinople, is it not fitly alledged,<note place="margin">Decr. lib. 1 de major. &amp; obed. can. Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitae.</note> that <hi>God made two great lights, the Sunne, that is the Pope, the Moone, that is the Emperour,</hi> and conclude from thence, that as farre as the Sunne exceedeth the Moon in greatneſſe, ſo much leſſe is the dignity of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, in reſpect of the Popes.</p>
            <p>As for their tranſlations, printed in the French tongue, one may ſee by the Bible, printed at Paris, An. 1538. by Antony Bonnemere, dwelling on S. Hillary hill, in the Court of Albret, that there are, (beſide the falſe inſertions, which are here and there put in among the text) ſeverall omiſſions of whole verſes of the text, and others added, the one to obſcure the truth, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lay the foundation of their lyes. Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſhall ſuffiſe, out of a great multitude. Vpon the 2 Chapt. of Exod. where there is firſt mention made of Moſes; goeing beyond the Scripture, they ſpecify the name of his Father and Mother of the Daughter of Pharao, adding thereunto that Moſes did throw downe to the ground the Crowne, which the King of Ægipt, playing with him, had ſet upon his little head, upon which Crowne was made Hammon, one of their Gods, and that he broke it; upon which the Prieſt of Heliopolis ſhould ſay unto the King, this is the childe which God would have us kill, which will bring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Land of Egipt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20876:12"/>And to make experience, whether the childe did this maliciouſly, or out of innocence, they cauſed bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning coales to be brought before the childe; and the childe tooke one, and put it to his mouth, and burnt the tip of his tongue, and thence it came, he retained his whole life time a ſtammering ſpeech: And the reſt of the whole chapter is ſtuft with the like Fables. On the 32 chapter of the ſame impreſſion in the ſame booke, many other things are added unto it, that Aaron and Hur, reſiſteing the people of Iſrael, which did aſke Gods of them; the people were incenſed againſt them both, for denying of them, and that they did ſpitt ſo abundantly on the face of Hur, that they did ſmoother him, which Aaron ſeeing &amp; fearing the like, gave way to their importunity, and made the Goulden Kalf: that the powder of the Goulden Kalf, which Moſes cauſed to be burnt, being drunke by the Iſraelites in water, cauſed them to have gilded beards, which was a ſpeciall marke to know thoſe, which had worſhipped the Kalf: Theſe are Fables like to the Legends of the Saints.</p>
            <p>With the ſame conſcience have they proceeded in the New Teſtament; They interprete theſe words of Mar. 4. <hi>Repent, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand,</hi> thus, <hi>doe pennance, for the Kingdome of Heaven will approach, that is, you ſhall merit and gaine the Kingdome of Heaven:</hi> And that to ſhew that Paradiſe is purchaſed by good workes. In the 26. of the ſame Evangeliſt, one may finde 40 lines of ſtrange gloſſes amongſt the text. In the Goſpel of S. Luke, have they added unto the words
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20876:12"/>
pronounced by our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, unto the converted murderer, Luc. 23. <hi>thou ſhalt be with me this day in Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They have added unto it, <hi>for before the reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt, no man or Prophet entred into Heaven; but all the just were ſojourning hard by Hell, in a place like unto it, where they wayted that the Sonne of man ſhould pull them out of it, and where they had neither payne nor glory.</hi> Much to purpoſe, to prove the welt of the Fathers. In the firſt to the Corinths, you finde in the Greek text.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14, 18.</note> 
               <hi>I give thankes vnto my God, that I ſpeake more languages then you all;</hi> For to excuſe themſelves of that text, that they ſpeake in their ſervice a language, that others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, and that it ſuffiſeth that it be underſtood of God, they have tranſlated it, <hi>I thanke my God, which ſpeaketh the languages of us all.</hi> And in the following verſes, they have corrupted it, and willfully left out theſe words: <hi>to that end, that I may alſo instruct the rest;</hi> and in place of <hi>five words,</hi> have they ſet downe <hi>ten words;</hi> and in ſtead of <hi>ten thouſand in a strange language,</hi> they write <hi>five of ſeverall languages;</hi> and all this, for feare leaſt their ſervice in a ſtrange language ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by theſe words of the Apoſtle: In the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, after theſe words, at the end of the 17. verſe of chapt. 10. <hi>And their ſinnes and iniquities will I remember no more;</hi> preſently followeth upon it: <hi>Now, where remiſsion of theſe is, there is no more offering for ſinne,</hi> verſe. 18. They have alltogether ſkipped this verſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it overthrowes directly the pretended ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and conſequently is againſt the prayers for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20876:13"/>
the dead, and their annuall prayers for the deceaſed. By theſe few obſervations, (for when ſhould one have done in quoteing the infinit number of others?) one may judge of the good fayth of the Doctors of the Romiſh Religion, which are not aſhamed publickly to write in the Preface of the ſaid Bible, in this manner: <hi>you may read this preſent book, which is the holy Bible, which was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated out of Latin into French, without any thing</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Nota.</note> 
               <hi>put to it, ſave the very truth, as it is in the Lattin Bible, nothing is</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nota.</note> 
               <hi>left out, ſave that which ſhould not be tranſlated, and this tranſlation is not made for the Clergie men, but for laymen, meane Devotaries, and Hermites, which have not the ſchollerſhip they ought to have;</hi> &amp; becauſe none ſhould accuſe thoſe of the Reformed Religion, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get new accuſations, againſt thoſe of the contrary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, behould ſome other words of the Preface: <hi>And this French Bible is firſt reprinted by command of the moſt Chriſtian Prince of France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">He raignd An. 1459.</note> Charles <hi>the eight of that name, and afterward it was corrected and reprinted;</hi> Marke <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected,</hi> whence we have good cauſe to ſuſpect, that in the time of that good King it was honeſtly tranſlated, without addition, ſubſtraction, or gloſſe with it, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the people by reading of it, comming to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the errours of that Doctrine, they could not revoke the impreſſion, but made a new one, ſuteing with the condition of the times, to prevent by a <hi>holy deceit</hi> (as they ſpeake in the Romiſh Religion) that the traffique of the ſoule ſhould not ceaſe, and that fertile field of pardons &amp; indulgences ſhould not lye untilled, and barren.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20876:13"/>With the like proceedings they furniſh themſelves, to make the Fathers and ancient Doctors in the church fruitleſſe, to diſcover their lyes, to that end, that the clearer ſighted, and thoſe that are not of the <hi>ſimple De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votaries,</hi> that is to ſay, ignorant ſort, ſhould not marke, that the judgements of thoſe good men were in many things contrary unto the Novelties and impieties, which after their time came up, and are taught unto this day in the Romiſh Religion; and that is the cauſe moveing them by a malicious art, to caſtrate the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, haveing blotted out whatſoever was found in their writeing, not to be conformable unto the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Counſell of Trente: And the workemen unto whom the commiſſion of ſo meritorious a deed was graunted, ſeeing they could not accompliſh their work, without makeing too great inſciſions, they have deviſed by <hi>an artificiall invention, either to denye or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, whatſoever any of theſe Fathers have written, or at leaſt to give it a favorable interpretation thereof.</hi> Theſe are their propper words, ſpeaking of Bertram Prieſt, in their <hi>index expurgatorius,</hi> printed at Antwerp, by Plantin, 1571. by commaunde of the King of Spaine, under the government of Duc d'Alva, as alſo an other Regiſter of books prohibited, a year afore: ſo are alſo the other <hi>Indices expurgatorij,</hi> that is to ſay, a regiſter of bookes, that muſt be repurged; printed in Spaine, ſuch alſo as were printed in Italy, or in that of Venice An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 1619. firſt made by the authority of Pope Pius the fourth, augmented by Sixtus the fifth, and laſtly viewd, &amp; publiſhed by commaund of Clement the eight, p. 19.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20876:14"/>
you ſhall finde theſe words: <hi>One ought alſo to blot out all the words of the holy Scripture, which are wickedly applyed againſt the ſound vſe of them. Such alſo as are wreſted to an intention, contrary to the opinion of the Doctors and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furder, and that which aggravates their enormity is, that there is this day in the Romiſh Religion, one of the greateſt Sacrileges that can be committed againſt the expreſſe commaund of God;<note place="margin">Deut. 4, 2.</note> 
               <hi>neither to adde nor to diminiſh unto the word which he had commaund<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d us. Adde not unto his words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30.6</note> 
               <hi>leaſt he reproove thee, and thou be found a lyar.</hi> And an obſtinate ſleighting of the threatnings, which God denounces againſt ſuch audacious men, with a proteſtation to execute them, as you may ſee in the Revelation.<note place="margin">Revel. 22.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>If any one ſhall adde vnto theſe things, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues that are written in this booke; and if any one ſhall take away from the words of this booke of this Prophecy, God ſhall take away his part out of the booke of life, and out of the Holy Citty, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence could proceed that horrible prudence ſo imprudently, to change the very words of the Holy Scripture, and to make it legittimate, but from a deſire which they have, to maintaine the people in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Kingdom of Antichriſt. And that is the wiſdom and prudence from below, that without any apprehenſion of the foreſayd threatnings, they have croſſed out the ſecond out of the Law of the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,<note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> which forbiddes <hi>to make Images or reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of things which are in Heaven or in the Earth, or in the water vnder the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> a croſſing out done, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20876:14"/>
entertaine the ſervice of the Creature, in the opinion of the ignorant: as if it made a part of Gods ſervice; and yet it is a thing moſt opppſite to his glory: For in Eſay he ſayth: <hi>My glory will I not give unto another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 42.8.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my prayſe to graven images.</hi> In the mean while, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall examine well, the whole Religious ſervice of the Romiſh Church, ſhall know, that it leanes more towards the Creature then towards the Creatour: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Almanacks of every nation, in which there is never a day, which doth not celebrate a particular ſaint: beſides theſe which are combined with others, and thoſe that comeing too late, could get no place; unto whome, notwithſtanding for recompenſe, they have eſtabliſhed a great ſolemnity; on which day they ſerve them together; unto the beſt qualified have they diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted the dayes, dedicated the Churches, conſecrated the Images, given the Ornamets, and beſides, in the invocations, which they make before their Images, they attribute ſuch titles unto them, which appartaine onely to God: yea in the Churches they have erected Images of thoſe things, which were never ſeene: all this directly againſt the ſecond commandement of the firſt Table, wherein God expreſly forbiddes, to make ſuch to fall downe before them, or performe unto them any ſervice, and therefore they have taken away that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from the peoples knowledge, for there is never a booke of devotion amongſt them in any lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage whatſoever, which containeth that commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; God then hath forbidden them, but the Romiſh Religion approves of them, becauſe they are the books
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20876:15"/>
of the Layics, that is of the ignorant, whome they commaund to travell, every where, unto ſeverall pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, farre, and neare, for to viſit ſeverall images: And in this regard, I cannot alltogether condemne them, who (ſpeaking of the Romiſh Church) ſay that the Religion there taught, is imaginary, and painted; For whereſoever you caſt your eyes, it every where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundes with pictures and images: Their Temples are full, within, without, or above; their Altars loaden with images, the leaves of the Altars painted with Images; their robes and weeds embrodred with images, the glaſſes alltogether darkened by the multitude of the painted images, their bookes of Devotion, the Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke, Breviaryes, Mattins, all full of images; their beads hanging on their neck, or girdle, adorned with images; their Pilgrims, comeing from S. Iames, or S. Michiles, or from elſe-where, burdened with images; the doores of their houſes clapt full with papers of the Fraternity; their cubbards in their chambers, and their cabinets furniſhed with images; and where ſhall one finde a place amongſt them, that is not therewith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right?</p>
            <p>Iuſtly then (ſayd hee) that this Religion is nothing but painting and imagination; For witneſſe of the wrath of God againſt Idolaters, one may read the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable puniſhment of the Children of Iſrael, who with their heart did worſhippe the true God, though it were under the ſimilitude of a Kalfe,<note place="margin">Exod. 32.4, 5</note> when 'tis ſayd, <hi>to morrow is a ſolemne Feast unto the Lord, &amp;c. Behould thoſe Gods that brough you out of the Land of Egypte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20876:15"/>In the Romiſh Religion, they paynt God the Father in their Churches, in the ſtreets, they hang his image for a ſigne at the Tavernes, with the image of the Sonne, and the H. Ghoſt; And under it is written, in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and the name of the Maſter of that place is called by his neighbours, the Maſter of the Trinity, as they call one, the Maſter of the Goulden Lion, or the like. To paint the Deity, and to make it reſemble a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is not that on a purpoſed will to ſinne againſt that which Moſes tould the people of Iſraell, when he appeared before the Lord in the Mount Horeb? <hi>The Lord ſpake vnto you out of the middest of the fire:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4, 12 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>yee heard the voice of the words, but ſaw no ſimilitude, onely a voice;</hi> And a little furder: <hi>Take yee therefore good heede vnto your ſelves, (for yee ſaw no manner of ſimilitude on that day that the Lord ſpake vnto you in Horeb, out of the middeſt of the fire,) least yee corrupt your ſelves, and make you a graven image, the ſimilitude of any figure, the likeneſſe of male or female, &amp;c.</hi> And our Saviour Chriſt, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming this Doctrine, addeth:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1, 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>No man then hath ſeene God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I hould the Romiſh Religion for Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, for image and idoll differ not but in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, the one being Greeke, and the other Latin, in which<note n="‖" place="margin">Quae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurus tota ſunt Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti tomi i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magines quae idola nominant.</note> Cicero expounds the word <hi>Idolum</hi> by Image, and to eſchew all ambiguity in words, God added the word of <hi>ſimilitude or likeneſſe,</hi> and afterward, <hi>what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi> So that I follow the inſtruction of S. Iohn:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6, 16 2 Ioh. 5, 21</note> 
               <hi>Little Children keepe your ſelves from idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20876:16"/>The Romiſh Religion deprives our Saviour Chriſt of a part of his glory, for to honour the Creatures with all, joyning companions with him, in the buſines of interceſſion, as Angells, men, women, trees, Iron, Cloathes: Their manuals of Devotion and Prayer-bookes are full of Hymnes, made to Saints. They ſay unto the wood of the Croſſe, (ſeverally conſidered from the perſon of Chriſt)<note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <p>In the Hymne, vixilla Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deunt.</p>
                  <p>Offi. Beat. Mar. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. 1601.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Increaſe righteouſneſſe unto the good; and give grace vnto the ſinnefull.</hi> In the prayer they putt up unto Chriſt they ſay: <hi>Lord graunt vnto us that thoſe, which come to adore thy holy Croſse, may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the bonds of their ſinnes.</hi> They attribute unto <hi>the thornes of the Crowne of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Offic. B. virg. Mar. Fol. 265. quel le Spine cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deli ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundal cuor mio ogni ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia.</p>
                  <p>Sanctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Dei nappa, ſancta ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darij, ora pro nobis.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>power to convert the heart, to purge it from pride, and to deliver ſinners, in the day of judgement, from the confuſion they deſerve by their ſinnes.</hi> What could they ſay more unto the holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin? yea, what could they hope more of Chriſt? So alſo they worſhip the Napkin that ſerved Chriſt at the inſtitution of the Lords Supper, ſaying: <hi>Most holy Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin of God praye for us;</hi> yea the Monkes of Fons have ſome Reliques of it: They of Cahors doe pray unto the holy Kercher, yea pray to the Lord by <hi>the vertue of the ſame Kercher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such devotion towards the Creatures, makes me marvaill, that the Romiſh Religion hath not made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles of Fayth then did the Apoſtles, as they have made the commandements of the Church equal, with the commandements of God; For ſince they call upon the Creatures, yea ſome of them unanimated things, it is a ſigne that they beleeve, and put their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20876:16"/>
truſt in them, they ſhould ſay then: I beleeve in the Croſſe, I beleeve in the Nayls, I beleeve in the Thorns, I beleeve in the wood and ſtone, I beleeve in our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſo make a new Creed; If then they doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve on them, how ſhall they call upon them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fayth.<note place="margin">Ro, 10, 14</note> For (ſayth Paul) <hi>how ſhall they call on him on whome they have not beleeved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the tittles, they attributed to the Lady Mary, they are blaſphemous againſt God, for that which belongs unto him alone, they aſcribe unto the virgin Mary, in the Songs, made to her praiſe; They make her everlaſting, before all ages, that Kings raigne by her, and give all the glory unto her, which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth onely unto the Father, Sonne, and H. Ghoſt, ſtileing her the mother of mercy, takeing away of ſinnes, ſanctifying the hearts. And unto her honour (though to the great diſhonour of God) they have all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together perverted all the 150 Pſalmes of David; in which they have every where changed the name of <hi>Lord</hi> into <hi>Lady,</hi> as in the 110 Pſalm, which the Lord applyes to himſelfe:<note place="margin">Mat. 22, 44</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſpoke vnto my Lord ſit thou at my right hand,</hi> &amp;c. they have put into the new Pſalm-booke: <hi>The Lord ſayd unto my Lady</hi> (that is unto the Virgin Mary) <hi>ſit thou at my right hand, &amp;c.</hi> If ſhe be then at the right hand of God, ſhe is in ſo great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of glory, as Chriſt himſelf: For he is no where elſe ſet but at the right hand of God, as ſayth the Creed: He ſits at the right hand of God; and Pſalm 57. in place of <hi>God,</hi> they have put: <hi>Lady have pitty on me! O Lady! have pitty on me, for my ſoule hopes in thee;</hi> and ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20876:17"/>
the whole Pſalmes through: She is to them <hi>the Queene of Heaven, the Gate of Paradiſe, the Fountain of life, mercy, grace, ſalvation to all thoſe that hope in her;</hi> titles onely, fitting the ſole Redeemer of the world.</p>
            <p>They beſtow no leſſe honour upon the Saints, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized by them, unto whome they diſtribute (as ſeemeth) good unto them, either greater or ſmaller charges: S. Nicolas is Preſident of the Navigation, S. George of the Fruits of the Earth, S. Rocus of the Peſt, S. Fremin of the Gout. S. Main of the Scabs, S. Eloy of the Horſes, S. Antony of the Hogges; There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hath not his protectour, even unto the pulletts, which have S. Leodigar, to defend them from the pip, and ſo of all the reſt. And by ſuch coards of Superſtitious Idolatry, they binde men to the invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Creature, and turne them away from the worſhip of the Creatour.</p>
            <p>And whoſoever would read the bookes of thoſe Spirits, that have alltogether erred from the truth, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died for the honour of their Saints; one may find, that they made them fouler in their actions, then the moſt infamous perſons: One may ſee in the booke of<note n="‖" place="margin">Printed at Ments 1612.</note> 
               <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplus,</hi> of the Miracles of our Lady Mary, in the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of<note n="†" place="margin">Printed at Antw. 1605.</note> Caeſarius, in the ſecond Tome of the flowr of Examples, printed at Roan, Anno 1616: that the Lady Mary, being ayded by Angells, did favour unto ſeverall whores, that were her Devotaries, a happy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance; ſupplying their places in the Monaſtery, whileſt they went many yeares revelling with their Ruffians; and for to imitate her other Saints, would be no leſſe courteous.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20876:17"/>Is that to honour the memory of the Holy Virgin? it is rather by the like hope of her favour, to relaxe the bridle to all kinde of looſenes. It is an horrour to ſee ſuch things taught in the writeings of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>Theſe Saints are become heads of the Orders, every one haveing their proſelites or Devotaryes, every one their particular government, habit, colour, different fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and by that diſtinguiſhed in the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, like as the Lackeys by their Liveryes in the Court of Kings and Princes. They give them the tittles of <hi>Fathers</hi> &amp; <hi>Mothers,</hi> not as unto ſuch as are inſtructours &amp; Adminiſtratours, under the charge of others, but as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as have engendred this <hi>Religious poſterity</hi> unto God, againſt that which our Saviour expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth, in Mat. 23. <hi>Call no man here vpon Earth your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> The one hath S. Francis for their Father, the other S. Dominicus; others ſuch as came afterwardes, as S. Ignatius, lately canonized by the importunity of the Ieſuites. And the Souveraine Father of all theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is the Pope; For he it is that bleſſed them firſt, and afterward canonizeth them, that is, bringeth them into the ranck and catalogue of the Saints. Therefore he by prerogative, beares the name of <hi>Father,</hi> with that adjective of <hi>Holy,</hi> yea in the abſtract it ſelfe <hi>his Holines,</hi> as they ſpeake of God, <hi>his Deity,</hi> or his <hi>Bounty:</hi> For when one ſpeaketh unto the Pope, he ſayth: <hi>Holy Father,</hi> a tittle which our Saviour Chriſt gave unto his Father,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17, 11</note> ſaying: <hi>Holy Father, keepe them in thy name.</hi> But the Pope ſuffers himſelfe to be called in the Superlative
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20876:18"/>
degree,<note place="margin">In the Gloſſe Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>moſt Holy Father;</hi> and why not, ſince he ſuffers himſelfe to be called <hi>God,</hi> yea <hi>our Lord God?</hi> He vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe to have all power in Heaven &amp; in Earth, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. of the holy Ceremonies, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. He gloryeth that by the abundance of his power he can diſpenſe with the Lawes, yea that he is above the Lawes; he will have us to receave the holy Scripture, becauſe the Pope hath pronounced his ſentence of them. He names himſelfe the <hi>Bridegrom of the Church, the Lion of Iudah, the Roote of David, the Saviour of Sion;</hi> Titles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing onely to Chriſt. Bellarmine ſayth: <hi>that the Church is the ſpouſe of the Pope, yea (Chriſto ſecluſo)</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration of Chriſt: He vaunts himſelf <hi>to have all the power of Lawes within his owne boſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Canon, <hi>Si Papa,</hi> in the 40 diſtinction, he exempts himſelfe from the judgements of men, whatſoever he doe. Theſe are the proper words of the Canon: <hi>If the Pope be found negligent of his, and his Bret<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rens ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, unproffitable and ſlow in his worke, and concealing the good, (which is moſt hurtfull to himſelf and others) in the meane while he leads whole bands of innumerable people with him to the firſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1. E. the Devill.</note> 
               <hi>Slave of Hell, for to be beaten eternally of him, with ſeverall blowes; No man may preſume to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend his faults; becauſe he that muſt judge all men, ought not to be judged of any perſon, except he be found to erre from the Fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this laſt cloſe it appeares, that at that time, they thought the Pope might be an Heretick, and now they thinke, he cannot erre; behould a manifeſt contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: A great number of other obſervations upon this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20876:18"/>
ſubject, doe offer themſelves, both in the Canons and in the writeings of the new Doctors of the Romiſh church; whence may be eaſily inferred, that he, which is ſo eminent in pride, ought not to take it in ill part, if they tell him, that one may juſtly preſume, that it is of him, that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, 2 Theſſ. chap. 2. ſeeing he carryeth himſelfe, as if he were God, in take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him the title of God, and attributeth unto himſelf ſuch a power, for <hi>he vaunteth himſelfe to have all power in Heaven or Earth.</hi> In the firſt booke of the Holy Ceremonies, Sect. 7. Chapt. 6. witneſſe, Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the third, in the Bulle, which is in the third Tome of the Counſells, who graunteth increaſe of honour, and a degree in Heaven above others, unto thoſe who ſhall goe beyond ſea to warre: And ſeeing himſelfe crowned with a triple-crowne, which they call, <hi>the Kingdome,</hi> he receaveth with contentment, as by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of his Souveraine power, this ſalution: <hi>Know that you are the Father of Princes, and of Kings, the Governour of the World, and the Liftenant of Christ here vpon Earth.</hi> And what would Boniface the 8. witneſſe leſſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? (by report of Charles of Moulin, Doctor in Law, Counſeller of France and Germany fol. 595.) the ſayd Boniface, to declare himſelfe to be Lord and Soveraigne over all men, in all things, whether Spirituall or Temporall, on the day of Iubile, Anno 1300.) of which he was the firſt inſtitutor, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be celebrated every<note n="‡" place="margin">After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 6. did reduct it to 50 yeare, and afterward Sixtus 4. to 25 year, which was An. 1475.</note> hundred yeare) did ſhew himſelfe unto a great confluxe of people, upon a ſtage, cloathed in the habit of a Pope, like to a Pagan
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20876:19"/>
Prieſt, haveing three Crownes on his head, and next day in a worldly habit of an Emperour, crowned and armed, haveing a naked ſword in one hand, and the Globe of the World in the other hand, ſpeaking aloud theſe words: <hi>Behould 2 ſwords, thou ſeeſt S. Peter, thy Succeſſour, and thou Chriſt, behouldest thy Vicar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to ſhut the mouth of thoſe, which draw into queſtion the right of Soverainty to the temporall things, which he attributeth unto himſelfe, as well as unto the ſpirituall; within two yeares after he made an Edict, which he publiſhed for an Article of Fayth, and neceſſary to ſalvation, upon penalty of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Such proceedings ſavour not the ſweet ſmell of Chriſt, who liveing in the world, ſayd to his auditors: <hi>learne of me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11, 29</note> 
               <hi>to be meek &amp; lowly of heart.</hi> Neither did they agree with the humble title of the ſayd Pope, which he uſed in the writeing of a letter to Phillip the Fayre, King of France; qualifying himſelfe with the title of <hi>Biſhop, and Servant of the Servants of God.</hi> The ſame pompe and magnificence in that Soveraine power, (in the fruition whereof the Succeſſours of the ſaid Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face have maintained themſelves) is ſeen enough, that though they write themſelves, <hi>the Servants of Servants of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> yet in effect they pretend to be <hi>the Lord of Lords of thoſe that be the Servants of Christ,</hi> and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it plainly to the Emperour, Kings, and Princes, preſent at his inauguration, cauſing them as Lackeys to hould the ſtirrop, when they mount a horſeback, makeing them to take the bridle of the horſe, to lead him apart on his way, <hi>in token of ſubmiſsion.</hi> And if
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20876:19"/>
he cauſe himſelfe to be carryed in a chayr, foure of the moſt qualified, whether Emperour or Kings, take him upon their ſhoulders, aſſiſted by foure ſtrong ſervants, for to helpe them, to beare the heavines of the lead.</p>
            <p>And whileſt the Pope dines, being ſet alone at table, the Biſhops and Cardinalls on two other tables, each according to their dignity: the mightieſt, and moſt noble amongſt the temporall Lords, though they were <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves, ſerve in their owne perſon to the Pope. When an Emperour muſt be Crowned, and he come to Rome, to receave the Romiſh Crowne, comeing neare the place, the Pope is ſet upon a ſtage, compaſſed about with Cardinalls, the Emperour lighting downe, as ſoone as he perceives his Holineſſe, boweth his knee to the ground, bare-headed, ſhewes him great reverence; and approaching nearer to his Throne, bowes againe his knee to the ground; at laſt comeing to the feet of the Pope, he kiſſeth them for devotion, in honour of the Saviour. All theſe things are evident ſignes, that he lifteth himſelf above the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraine powers of the Earth. And if his pride had beene limited in putting his foot upon the neck of the Emperours, as did moſt arrogantly Pope Alexander the third, unto Emperour Frederic Barberouſſe, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the gate of the Temple of S. Mark, at Venice, ſpeaking theſe words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 91, 13</note> as if they were written on his behalfe: <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lion and Adder, and the yong Lion, &amp; the Draggon, thou ſhalt trample under foot;</hi> one might impute this action for a humane argument:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20876:20"/>
But to lift himſelf above him whome he worſhippeth and acknowledgeth for his Creatour, it is to make himſelf a fellow ſinner to thoſe, of whome Iude ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Iud. 8.5.</note> 
               <hi>which deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeake evill of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes,</hi> and followers of the Angells, <hi>which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their owne habitation:</hi> For this is donne at Roome, at cleare noone-day, in ſight of more then 10000 witneſſes, who from all corners of Italy flocke thither, to ſee that Feaſt, and to receave there the bleſſing of the new <hi>Succeſsour of S. Peter, the Vicar of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> When he marcheth thus, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied and led by Cardinals, which are Princes of that Court, ſerved by Emperour, and Kings, carried upon their ſhoulders, in token of their Religious piety: <hi>His conſecrated Hoste,</hi> (which he ſayth he beleeves to be <hi>his God, his Creatour, and his Redeemer</hi>) is ſent before, as it were to prepare him the way, very plainely accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied; For they that goe before it, are the porters of the Cardinalls, here and there amongſt the people; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them follow in order the Barbour and Taylour of the Pope, with their budgetts, the Family of the Pope, and the common Gentry, the Nevewes and Coſins of my Lords the Cardinalls, the footbench of the Pope, carried upon a white horſe, lead by one of the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, afterward a few runners with Standards of ſeveral colours; after them the Chamberlins with the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of better faſhion then the former, after them two Purſuivants, with their ſtaves in their hands, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a troupe of ſervants of the Pope, carrying ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten torches in their hands before the Sacrament, two
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20876:20"/>
houſhould Chapplaines, with two ſilver Lanterns, on horſeback, and afterward commeth the Sacrament up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a white horſe, haveing a ſilver bell about his neck, lead by the ſervant of the Chaplaine; afterward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the Chapplaine himſelfe on horſeback; after him follow the Singers, the Clerkes, and Auditors of the Chamber, there is the whole traine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But in the traine of the Pope are the Prelates, Abbots, Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Patriarchs, Cardinalls, in the traine two Deacons, aſſiſteing the Pope, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the Pope himſelf, on a white horſe, embrodered and coſtly adorned, under a Canopie, borne up by eight great Lords and Ambaſſadours; and compare the train of the one with the traine of the other, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudeing which is done to the Pope, with ſmall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance &amp; ſtate they worſhip their God with; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe one may judge, that the Pope is the Maſter, and God his Servant. The ſhort rehearſall hereof is true; and whoſoever pleaſe to read it, I can open unto him the booke of the Romiſh Pontificalls, printed at Venice, Anno 1582. dedicated unto Pope Gregory the thirteenth of that name.</p>
            <p>Adde unto the former thinges that divine power which the Pope attributes unto himſelfe, and which flowes by his influence (as from a ſpring) from him upon all Prieſts of the Romiſh Religion, to be able to change the nature of things, to deprive them of their ſubſtance, and to ſubſtitute others in their place; The accidents of thoſe things that periſh, yet remaining, to cover their other corporall ſubſtance with, which ſhall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20876:21"/>
have two accidents, in colour, taſte, and form, of which the ſenſes can have no knowledge, either workeing, or elſe pretending to worke thoſe things, which God never made, and unto which nothing is found like, amongſt all the miraculous workes, of which the holy Scripture makes mention, either in the Ould or New Teſtament: a power unheard of, whence the new and unknowne worke is called <hi>Tranſubstantiation,</hi> and to perſwade the poore ignorant people thereunto, they take away the uſe of their eyes, taſteing, tongue, and hands, and deprive them of the liberty, to diſcerne and judge of things, according to their naturall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, what they are, and to commaund that they ſhould beleeve, that that which was black was white; and that they muſt follow him that goes before, though it were otherwiſe againſt the judgement of their owne eyes. This is one of the rules, the thirteenth in order of thoſe, that eſtabliſh the Ieſuites, to cleave to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Romiſh Church, in theſe words: <hi>Finally, that we may keepe the conformity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exerc. ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual. ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietat. Ieſ. authore Ignatio de Loyola Viennae Auſt. An. 1563. fol. 139. b.</note> 
               <hi>and agreement of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with the Catholick Church, if ſhe conclude any thing to be black, that we ſee is white, we must graunt with her, that it is black;</hi> To attribute unto her ſelfe ſuch power, is not that to equaliſe her with God? and in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, to lift her ſelf up above Angells, Thrones, Dominions yea above the Virgin Mary, and which is moſt horrible above Ieſus Chriſt our Creatour, and to dare publiſh this in bookes, is not this enough, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Religion, doeing theſe things, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyffered of S. Iohn in his Revelation? <hi>by that woman
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20876:21"/>
ſet upon a ſcarlet coloured beaſt, full of names of blaſphemy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17, 3. and 13, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and the beast that opened his mouth in blaſphemy against God, to blaſpheme his Name, and his Tabernacle, and them that dwelt in Heaven.</hi> Now, the Pope, in quality of a Prieſt, and all other Prieſts doeth thus, conſenting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bookes, made by men of their order, wherein all theſe blaſphemyes are found, and to point this out, as it were with fingers, that they may not thinke, we onely diſcourſe of generallityes, or certaine heare-ſayes, or unwritten words, read one of the moſt famous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatours, upon the Canon of the Maſſe, namely Gabriel Biel, a German of Nation, who lived, and was much eſteemed of Pope Alexander the ſixth, Anno 1494. his booke afterward reviewed and corrected, was printed at Lions Anno 1527. one ſhall finde there, leſſon 4. fol. 5. and 6. many, and ſeverall reaſons, to raiſe the dignity of the Prieſts, above all Creatures in Heaven and in Earth, amongſt the reſt, <hi>that by the words of the Prieſt, the Heavens are opened, paſſe through the throng of Angells, comeing to the Queene of Heavens, and Lady of the world, though ſhe exceed all other Creatures in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace, yet gives place to thoſe which have the holy Government of the Church, or the administration of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery committed vnto them.</hi> And further: <hi>Hearken there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye Prieſts, taſters to the true Salomon, and Chamberlains of Chriſt.</hi> You may alſo read an ould booke, called <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacrim conſcientiae,</hi> printed at Paris by Denis Roce, you finde there, that the author,<note place="margin">Lavacr. conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae cap. 5.</note> ſpeakeing of the dignity of Prieſts, ſets the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> above Kings &amp; Angels, at laſt above the virgin Mary, in theſe words: <hi>He is more excellent then the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20876:22"/>
moſt worthy Virgin, in that he creates the body of Christ, yea he prevaileth more on Earth, then the moſt powerfull Angell of Heaven, yea then the Virgin Mary her ſelfe, for vnto thee, O Prieſt, thy Lord and thy God becometh obedient, for to be preſent at the time of conſecration.</hi> And ſpeakeing of the Prieſts they bring in Chriſt, ſpeakeing theſe words to them: <hi>I have given you more power, then vnto all the Angells and Saints of Paradiſe, yea vnto my beloved Mother, to witt, in the conſecration of the Eucharist, wherein I am allwayes obedient unto you, as well vnto the wickedest, &amp; moſt roguiſh Prieſt, as unto the holieſt Sainct, and you have I exalted above all Creatures;</hi> Beſides, <hi>the Priest is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier then a King, holier then an Angell, and a Creatour of his Creatour</hi> And in another booke of the ſaid age, called <hi>Stella Clericorum,</hi> the Prieſt is honoured with ſuch dignityes, that he is called, <hi>the Creatour of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and of all Creatures;</hi> Beſides, <hi>God hath preferred him above Angells, Thrones, and Dominions;</hi> Yet further, <hi>he that created me without my ſelf, is now created himſelfe by my meanes.</hi> All theſe bookes, without addition or exaggeration, have theſe ſame aforeſayd words in their writings; Could one adde to ſuch blaſphemies? Is it not good reaſon one ſhould abhorre, and avoid ſuch Religion? and renounce the head thereof? who exalteth himſelf above all power, either temporall or ſpirituall, above that which he confeſſeth to be God, and yet receaveth the title of God.</p>
            <p>As concerning the articles of Fayth, of which (with us) he &amp; his make profeſſion, the Doctrine of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Religion deſtroys many fundamentall points
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20876:22"/>
thereof: The Articles of Fayth (agreeing with the H. Scriptures) teach us, that Ieſus Chriſt is the Sonne of David, accordeing to the Fleſh, which he tooke upon him, in the wombe of the holy Virgin: the body which the Prieſt ears, at the celebration of the Maſſe, is not of the ſeed of <hi>David,</hi> but of the ſeed of corn, cam not forth out of the Matrix of the Virgin, neither was it there nouriſhed the ſpace of nine monthes, but was formed by the will of the Prieſt, (ſuch a conception was not by the Holy Ghoſt, but by the intention of the Prieſt, provided that he had an intention,) but was brought forth from two hot Irons, where it was formed, (ſuch a birth was not of the virgin,) its roundneſſe, whiteneſſe, flatneſſe, taſte, weight, are not accidents to an humane body, as Chriſt had, liveing in the world, and dying for us, neither the inconveniences ſuch an Hoſty is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto, as to be eaten of Wormes, Patrets, or Ratts, to rotte, to be ſwallowed into the ſtommack, and from thence to be caſt out otherwhere, to be broken, and to be caſt up againe by the Prieſt, are no proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes to a body, glorifyed, as that is of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, after his reſurrection: to be in a place, without takeing up of any ſpace, to be in ten thouſand mouths of communicants, which at the ſame houre keep their Eaſter in a great towne, and to become as it were infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit throughout whole Chriſtendome, ſtands not with the nature of a body; for infiniteneſſe is onely proper to the Deity, and thus attributeing unto the glorifyed body of our Lord an infiniteneſſe, they make a new Divinity; and generally beleeving this, they contradict
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20876:23"/>
an Article of the Creed that ſayth: <hi>He is ſet at the right hand of God the Father Almighty;</hi> as alſo oppoſite unto that which the Angells did ſpeake unto the Apoſtles, after the aſcenſion of our Lord,<note place="margin">Act. 1, 11.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhall come ſo as they ſaw him goeing to Heaven.</hi> But they ſaw him aſcend corporally; let them now bring us witneſſes, without gainſaying, which ſaw him deſcend corporally: it contradicts alſo that which the Apoſtle ſayeth, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of our Lord Ieſus, being raiſed againe. <hi>Wherefore henceforth know we no man after the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5, 16</note> 
               <hi>yea though we have knowne Christ after the flleſh, yet now henceforth know we him no more.</hi> If the Apoſtle had beleeved the preſence of Chriſt, bodily to be upon the Earth, he would not have ſayd: <hi>we know him no more after the fleſh;</hi> and Chriſt would not have ſaid:<note place="margin">Mat. 26, 11</note> 
               <hi>Me yee ſhall not have allwayes with you,</hi> if at the commaund of the Prieſt he were allwayes preſent at the Hoſt. He that would dive deeper into this matter, might bring to light ſo many abſurdityes, that thoſe which teach this doctrine, ſhould be convinced within themſelves, that like poore blind men, they have followed without knowledge thoſe which cauſed them to erre from the truth, contained in the ſaid Articles of Fayth.</p>
            <p>As for the Sacraments of the Baptiſme and the Lords Supper, (without examining the number, they adde unto them) they are in the Romiſh Church ſo corrupted, and maimed, in their adminiſtration, that he which ſhould compare them with the practiſe of the Apoſtle, and of the Primitive Church, ſhould finde ſuch difference, as betweene a true childe, and a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyted,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20876:23"/>
betweene a healthfull body, and a diſeaſed. Vnto the ſingleneſſe of Baptiſme, <hi>which is adminiſtred in ſingle water, in the name of the Father, of the Sonne, and of the Holy Ghost;</hi> how many noveltyes have they added unto it, of which they can ſhew no word nor example,<note place="margin">Salus me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris Ad ejicie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones, morboſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pellendos.</note> much leſſe any commaund in the word of God, nor in the purer ancient times: To witt, the conjuring of the water, ſalt and oyle; <hi>Of the ſalt, to be to all thoſe which vſe it, a ſaveing of ſoule and body; Of the water, to caſt out Devills, and take away ſickneſſes:</hi> Wherefore put they ſalt into the mouth of the infant preſented to the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?<note place="margin">Salutare ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad fugandum inimicum.</note> To what end ſay they theſe words to it: <hi>receave the ſalt of wiſdom?</hi> wherefore call they it <hi>a ſaving Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to drive away the Devill?</hi> Will they adde the ſalt unto it as the eight Sacrament? where ſhall they finde that <hi>God hath commanded it to be conſecrated by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, for the faithfull people?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Populo venienti ad Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem per ſervos ſuos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrari praecepit.</note> who tould them that the Devill is in the body of the infant newly borne? To commaund five times with a conjuration that evill Spirit to goe out; which might give occaſion to any one, for to aſke whether the Devill was within the body of the infant, whileſt the mother was with child of it, or whether he entred after it was borne; whence ſhould follow, either that the mother with the child had the devill within her, or that the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the infant dying in the mothers belly, is more happy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> its birth, ſeeing the devill makes his dwelling-place in that litle body after it is borne; as if God gave the Children of Chriſtians, as ſoon as they were borne, to the devil for a pray; If they denye the one or the other, to what end doe they commaund in the name of God the devill to com out of a body, into which he entred not?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:20876:24"/>This is then to take the name of God in vaine, in ſo many exorciſmes and adjurations, as they make with ſo many ſignes of the Croſſe reiterated. Who gave the Prieſt charge to putt his ſpittle in the eares and noſe of the infant,<note place="margin">In odore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuavitatis. Such ſpitle may be juſtly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for the infant, if the Prieſt be not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man.</note> 
               <hi>for a ſmell of a good ſavour?</hi> Who commaunded him to put the oyle upon the breaſt, &amp; betweene the ſhoulders of the infant? We read not that God commaunded thoſe things in the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nor Chriſt in Baptiſme, of which the Element, being water is unto us, by the waſhing of our bodyes; an externall ſigne of the cleanſing of our perſons, by the blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they in the Romiſh Church attribute ſuch vertue, unto the outward adminiſtration of the water, and to the intention of him that adminiſtreth, that they make the efficacy of the Baptiſme to depend ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely upon it; in ſo much that any one being Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with water, and not knoweing certainely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that Baptized did pronounce the words of the Baptiſme, with an intention to doe that which the Church doth, cannot be certaine that he is truely Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; and this outward adminiſtration of the water in Baptiſme, being judged by them neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that made them ſet downe theſe queſtions in their bookes:<note n="†" place="margin">Manipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum, made in the yeare 1333, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, 1476. dedicated to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Valence, cap. 2. de materia Baptiſmi.</note> 
               <hi>whether in want of water one may not vſe vrine, Pottage, Lee, Roſewater, ſnow-water, durt? whether one may caſt a childe into a well, if there were nothing to draw water withall; &amp; ſo to Baptize it? whether &amp; how one ought to Baptize a childe, comeing forth in the birth with the hand or foot, and not with the head, when there is daunger it
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20876:24"/>
would die in the mothers wombe.</hi> The ſame neceſſity being preſuppoſed, made them reſolve,<note n="†" place="margin">Pupilla oculi cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorum, made by a Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Vniverſity of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, An. 1385. Printed at Roan, 1510.</note> 
               <hi>to give-power to Baptize vnto women, children, not onely Chriſtians, but alſo into infidels, vnbaptized Hereticks, Iewes, Pagans; any wicked howſoever</hi> (then alſo unto ſorcerers) <hi>yea without excepting the Divells themſelves; provided they doe it by the commandement of God, and according to the order of the Church.</hi> Strange things; by their adjurations they make againſt the Devill, they pretend to caſt him out of the body of the infant; and notwithſtanding they will accept of a Baptiſme, performed by the Devill, upon condition that he hath had a good intention: But who ſhall be the Devills ſurety, that he hath done it according to the order of the Church, and from a good intention? I paſſe many other things over with ſilence, which might be worth the markeing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this ſubject.</p>
            <p>As for the Sacrament of the pretious body &amp; blood of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Romiſh Religion hath alltogether aboliſhed in effect, and hath not left any true token of that, which he ordained unto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; nor of that, which the Primitive Church for many hundred yeares hath practiſed. Our Saviour by this Sacrament hath inſtituted the commemoration of his death; the Churches for their conſolation have celebrated the memory thereof ſo many ages; but the Romiſh Church in ſtead of a Sacrament, hath brought in a Sacrifice, which they call <hi>Propitiatorie,</hi> that is, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing the wrath of God, for the ſinnes of the liveing and the dead, that is that which ſeemeth moſt ſtrange
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20876:25"/>
unto me, ſeeing Ieſus Chriſt as God; Therefore infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, as the Sonne of man, conceaved of the H. Ghoſt, without blemiſh, therefore juſt, holy, and perfect; and laſtly, as Mediatour betweene God and Men, partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of both natures, joyned together in the unity of his perſon; and that perſon haveing according to both his natures, all perfection, who by a voluntary yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſented himſelf to God for us, to ſatisfy his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in our name, hath had no defects or wants in his Kingly, Prieſtly, &amp; Propheticall office, neither by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in his benefites of protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To ſay the contrary, is to blaſpheme, &amp; accuſe him of inſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy; If he be then ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he is perfect, he hath left us the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing for to perfect, to our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor for the propitiation of our ſinnes; For the which no oblation more is to be done, ſeeing he hath obteined remiſſion for them; as witneſſeth the Apoſtle: <hi>Now where remiſsion of theſe is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10, 18</note> 
               <hi>there is no more offring for ſinne;</hi> therefore no more ſacrifice: whence I conclude to make ſacrificers, for ſucceſſours of Ieſus Chriſt in that office; that is to ranck them amongſt the offring Prieſts of the ould Teſtament, who by death were hindred to continue their charge: That is then to ſay, that Chriſt is not eternall; which is to belye the Scripture, which ſayth, <hi>that he is an High Prieſt for ever, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedec.</hi> And to reiterate the ſame Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the ſame end that Ieſus Chriſt did offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, is to ſay plainely, that he hath not ſatisfyed God his Father, and that is to accuſe his oblation to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective; which cannot be ſayd without blaſphemy; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20876:25"/>
if that be defective, and hath not been ſufficient to ſatisfie the Iuſtice of God his Father, offered by himſelf upon the Altar of his Croſſe, <hi>by the Eternall ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9, 14</note> who ſhall perſwade us, that an offering by the hand of a ſinnefull man could be pleaſing unto God? (but who dare ſay, that the Prieſt exceedeth Chriſt?) who ſhall then aſſure us of the remiſſion of our ſinns by ſuch a Sacrifice? whence I draw this conſequence, either, that there is not at all forgivenes of ſinnes, or that it muſt have been obtained by Ieſus Chriſt; and that in that Sacrifice, which he offerd unto God, in giveing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And that therefore there is no Sacrifice more to be offered, but one by a remembrance to be made of Chriſts Sacrifice, according to his ordinance, as that was done by the Primitive Church, and as it is yet ordinarily maintained in the Reformed Church.</p>
            <p>The Maſſe it ſelfe, examined by the word of God, ſhall be found not to be a propitiatory Sacrifice for ſinnes, as can be gathered by that which the Church of Roome ſayth of the Maſſe, that it is a Sacrifice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blood, that is, in which there is no death; and the Apoſtle in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes ſayth:<note place="margin">Heb. 9, 22.</note> 
               <hi>Without ſhedding of blood</hi> (that is without death) <hi>there is no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givenes of ſinnes.</hi> Whence I underſtand firſt, that it is falſe, that they ſay that the pretended Sacrifice of the Maſſe ſhould be the ſame which Chriſt made upon the Croſſe; for the difference ſtands upon a manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, the Sacrifice of Chriſt was with ſhedding of his blood, and that of the Maſſe is without ſhedding, then it is not the ſame; or elſe you muſt ſay that <hi>Yea
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20876:26"/>
and No, to affirm and to deny,</hi> are the ſame. Now from the paſſage of S. Paul, and the definition of the Maſſe I draw this argument, in the concluſion whereof I finde, that in the pretended Sacrifice of the Maſſe there is no forgivenes of ſinnes.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Where there is no ſhedding of blood, there is no forgivenes of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>In the Maſſe there is no ſhedding of blood; Ergo in the Maſſe there is no forgivenes of ſinnes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>To what end then doe they call the Maſſe a Sacrifice propitiatorie, or of appeaſement, ſeeing we know it is without ſatisfaction unto the Iuſtice of God? But it is without ſatisfaction, becauſe it is without death; for <hi>the wages of ſinne is death:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.23.</note> Therefore it is not propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie for the ſinnes of the liveing; much leſſe for thoſe which they imagine to be in purgatory. And ſeeing we beleeve the forgivenes of ſinnes, as we confeſſe in the Articles of Fayth; wherefore ſhould we make new Sacrifices to obtaine it? For we beleeve not that which is uncertaine, but that which is certaine, elſe it would be but uncertainty and no Fayth: we make a profeſſion of Fayth, yea of that Fayth, concerning the forgivenes of ſinnes, and ſeeing we have it in the the Church of Chriſt, there remaines no oblation more for ſinne; That is it which the Apoſtle teacheth us in theſe words:<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 18</note> 
               <hi>Now where remiſsion of theſe is, there is no more offring for ſinne.</hi> He had ſpoken in the verſe going before, of ſinnes and iniquityes which God had forgotten. From this paſſage then I forme this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereof the concluſion is, that in the Chriſtian
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20876:26"/>
Church, there is no oblation more to be made for ſinne.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Where there is forgivenes of ſinnes, there muſt be no more oblation for ſinne.</p>
               <p>But in the Chriſtian Church there is forgivenes of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Ergo, in the Chriſtian Church there is no more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blation for ſinne.</p>
            </q>
            <p>What will become then of the Maſſe, except they ſay it is not in the Chriſtian Church, but onely in the Church of Roome? But, for that I know, that the Maſſe deſtroyeth the aſſurance of our ſalvation, doth ruinate the foundation of Fayth, and is injurious unto the dignity of the perſon of our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, and blaſphemous againſt the perfectneſſe of his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; my conſcience obligeth me to renounce it; and to joyne my ſelfe to thoſe, who with devotion, at the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, which our Saviour inſtituted, keep a remembrance of his death, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that he haveing ſuffered it on the Croſſe, in which he perfected his onely Sacrifice, and that propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatorie to appeaſe the wrath of God;<note place="margin">Heb. 10, 14</note> 
               <hi>He hath by that one offering, perfected for ever them that are Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the vowes, unto which in the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion they oblige the conſciences, to the exact obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe things, which are not commaunded in the word of God, and to deprive themſelves of thoſe things, which are created for the Lawfull uſe of man, preferring certaine dayes before others, and haveing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20876:27"/>
neyther command nor example of thoſe things in the word of God, nor in the practiſe of the Primitive Church, neyther alſo of thoſe diſtinctions of Orders, of Devotaryes, which each of them have their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Patron; I finde that all theſe are human inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, proceeding from the ambition and vanity of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine men,<note place="margin">Col. 2, 18.</note> 
               <hi>which would rule over others, at their pleaſure, in a voluntary humility and worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, intrudeing into thoſe things, which they have not ſeen, vainly puft vp by their fleſhly minde;</hi> not permitting unto Chriſtians the liberty which Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed them, but deſireing to charge them with ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, <hi>Touch not, taſte not, handle not, which all are to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with the vſeing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2, 21</note> 
               <hi>after the Commandements and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines of men; which things indeed have a ſhew of wiſedom, in will-worſhippe, and humility, and neglecting of the body, not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is nothing but a vaine deceaving, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rudiments of the World, and not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſt. But thoſe ſhewes of Holineſſe, in theſe voluntary devotions, in ſtead of bringing men to the true humility of the Spirit, have filled them with pride, and an opinion of perfection, each of them, that were founders of thoſe noveltyes, make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their order ambitiouſly, more commendable by their ſtrictneſſe; in ſo much, that we dayly ſee one or other faſhion of a Religions habit come up, which never heretofore was knowne: Theſe diverſityes have brought ſo ſtrong a Iealouſie amongſt theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that they are come to enmity, envy, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20876:27"/>
partiallity, and to take upon them other Names then that of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eph. 1, 22</note> 
               <hi>whom God hath given above all things to be head of his Church.</hi> For the one will ſay (for which the Apoſtle reprooveth the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that were at Corinth,) <hi>I am Pauls, I am Apollos, I am Cephas, and I am Chriſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1, 12</note> now one claimes one head, another another. Bernardines, Auguſtines, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobines, Dominicans, Benedictians, Carmelites, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliers, and thoſe that will be eſteemed more then all the reſt, and are allwayes hated of the other Orders, have choſen the Name of Ieſus, calling themſelves his aſſociates, namely Ieſuites, for aſke them of what Order they are, they will anſwer, of the Society of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. The women muſt have their part, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, that no perfectneſſe to that devotion ſhould be wanting, for lack of that Company, which is ſo neceſſary for man, to ſweeten his life: The founders of theſe Orders, ſaw that it was not good, for man to be alone they made him a helpe, like to himſelf; in devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, habit, rule, of life, Beggery; yea not many yeares agoe, becauſe thoſe which call themſelves of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Ieſus; had no ſhee fellowes of the ſame name, there are a Company of Devotary women, which tooke upon them the ſame title, but becauſe that this ſeemed to be done by private Authority, it was wiſely condemned by the Pope, for feare leaſt that would inferre many daungerous conſequences; as is more largely contained in the Bull of <hi>Pope Vrban</hi> the eight, printed at Rome, by the Printer of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Chamber, 1631.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:20876:28"/>
               <note place="margin">Eſſe plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Dei noxias, quas ne ulterius ſe diffunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, radicitus evellendas &amp; extirpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</note>Theſe Religious women called themſelves <hi>Ieſuiteſſes, which Pope Vrban condemned, to be rooted out, as plants noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the Church of God.</hi> And all theſe Orders are bound by a ſolemne vow, to live in the ſtate of conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and are kept from the Holy Marriage, though they be not free from ſuch affections, which binde one to the Lawfull uſe of it, they that will profeſſe their veſſels in holineſſe, according to the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: <hi>That this is the will of God, even our Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4, 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>that we ſhould abstaine from fornication, that every one of us ſhould know, how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and honour.</hi> And that which he ſayth to the Corinths:<note place="margin">1 Co. 7, 8, 9</note> 
               <hi>To thoſe that are vnmarried and Widdows, if they cannot containe, that they marry; for it is better to marry then to burn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13, 4</note> As alſo to the Hebrews: <hi>Marriage is honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in all, and the bed vndefiled, but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let any body read the whole Ould and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament throughout, he ſhall not finde one word which tends to the forbidding of Marriage, nor one jot that commaunds the vow of perpetuall continence. The Prieſts and Prophets were married, as alſo the moſt part of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, as can be gathered by that which Paul ſayth, 1 Cor. 9.5. and Mat. 8.14. of the Mother in Law, that is of the Mother of the Wife, of the Apoſtle S. Peter, whome Chriſt healed of an ague.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, againſt the expreſſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the word of God, the Church of Roome forbiddeth Eccleſiaſticall perſons, of both ſexes, to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20876:28"/>
marry; againſt the Examples of the Prophets and Apoſtles in this matter; againſt the practiſe of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, which may be gathered by the reading of the Hiſtory. S. Paul did not forbid the Biſhopps Marriage, when he ordaines,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>that the Biſhop ſhould be the huſband of one Wife,</hi> &amp;c. which muſt not be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>of one Church onely</hi> (as doe thoſe which wreſt his words, as alſo other Scriptures to their owne condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) but of an eſpouſed wife; as appeareth by the compariſon he makes in the ſame place, betweene the Family of the Biſhop, and the Church which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto him: And thoſe who under the pretext of makeing the Eccleſiaſticall men leſſe buiſied in the affaires of this world, and more free to attend on ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, have forbidden them Marriage, have brought them into ſnares of thouſand wicked temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which make them committ ſuch horrible miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, the rehearſing whereof would make one ſh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke: how many ſmootherings of new-borne babes are there found, to recover the honour of thoſe that loſt it? It was not without great cauſe, that Pope Pius the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond (as teſtifyeth Platina, who hath written the lives of the Popes) ſaid, that if there were great motives to forbidde Prieſts to marry, for farre greater reaſons one ought to reſtore them their liberty againe; And S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard the Abbot, haveing examined well how neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Marriage is, to prevent that the Church of God might not be a place of all uncleane Spirits, ſayth flatly: <hi>Take from the Church the honourable Marriage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Cant. Salo. Ser. 66.</note> 
               <hi>and the Bed which is vndefiled, doe you not fill it with Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20876:29"/>
inceſtuous, effeminate, and Sodomitiſh perſons; finally, with all ſorts of filthineſſe? And ſince it could not be, but offences ſhould come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18, 7</note> 
               <hi>but woe unto them by whom they come;</hi> So muſt ſcandalls come, to verify that which the Propheticall Spirit of God hath revealed unto the Apoſtle Paul,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1. 3</note> where we read, that <hi>amongſt the Doctrines of the Devill,</hi> he forgetteth not to marke <hi>the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of marriage, and abſtinence from meats, which God hath created to be receaved with thankes-giveing, of them which beleeve and know the truth.</hi> And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard how can they excuſe before God that yoke which they would impoſe upon the conſciences? Since the Apoſtle manifeſts:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4, 4 5.</note> 
               <hi>That every Creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed, if it be receaved with thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveing, for it is ſanctified by the Word of God, and Prayer.</hi> As alſo to the Coloſſians: <hi>Let no man judge you in meat or in drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2, 16</note> 
               <hi>or in reſpect of an holy day, or of the New Moone, or of the Sabbath dayes.</hi> And to the Romans: <hi>That the Kingdom of God is not meat and drinke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 14, 17</note> 
               <hi>but righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse, and peace, and joy, in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And to the Corinths:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8, 8</note> 
               <hi>Meat commendeth us not to God, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if we eate, are we the better, neither if we eate not are we the worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who maketh them ſo bould to bring them under the yoke of bondage, whome Chriſt hath freed? And who being ranſomd by him, muſt not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of their libertyes, which he hath purchaſed them? And who hath given them that power, to oblige men by ſolemne vowes, upon paine of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to tranſgreſſe theſe commaundements, which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20876:29"/>
the Apoſtle ſayeth to <hi>proceed from ſuch as have depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Fayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim 4.1.2</note> 
               <hi>giveing heed vnto ſeduceing Spirits and Doctrines of Devills, ſpeaking lyes in hypocriſie, &amp;c.</hi> People that puniſh more rigourouſly the tranſgreſſions of the commandements of men, then of the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, as can be ſeene in the taxation of the Apoſtolicall Chauncery, printed by Galeot du Pre, in the great Pallace Hall at Paris, Anno 1533. wherein the diſpenſations and abſolutions for paricide, are better cheap, then to have a graunt to eat fleſh on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden dayes. For Example, the abſolution of a woman that hath taken a drinke, for to void her living Childe, is taxed but to 18 pence tournois, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts; and a diſpenſation not to be obliged to faſt certaine dayes, and to have leave to eate cheeſe, is taxed to 66 pence: If a Layman kill a Prieſt, or a Clark, muſt pay 6 ſhillings, muſt doe publick pennance, and muſt be beaten at five Pariſh Churches. A huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band that hath beaten his Wife, being with Childe, ſo that ſhe have a miſchaunce, ſhall pay two ſhillings: He that ſhall counterfeyt the Apoſtolicall Letters, muſt pay 9 ſhillings. If any one kill their Father, Mother, Brother, or Siſter, muſt pay 16 or 17 pence; and one that hath gotten his Orders by Simony, 17 ſhillings and a groat.</p>
            <p>By theſe few Examples one may ſee that ſinnes are ſet at a certaine price; and thoſe which are againſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſtitutions, at a higher rate then thoſe which are contrary to the commandements of God. We read not that ſuch pecuniary fines were impoſed by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20876:30"/>
the Apoſtles upon the poore ſinners, that which we read in the Goſpell is: Repent, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand. If yee repent not, yee ſhall all periſh;<note place="margin">Act. 3, 19</note> 
               <hi>Repent yee therefore, &amp; be converted, that your ſinnes may be blotted out,</hi> and ſuch like wordes; Where we find nothing ſpoken of mony payed for ſinnes. Such proceedings are contrary to that which the Apoſtle requireth in a Biſhop, that he be not covetous of filthy lucre: Me thinkes, it is a thing not well beſeemeing a Prelate, to receive ſuch forfeitures, as a Iuſtice of Peace ſhould exact of ſuch as infringe the Politick Lawes. To ſuch Prelates may be applyed that which God ſaid to Eſay:<note place="margin">Eſa. 57, 17</note> 
               <hi>For the iniquity of his covetouſneſſe was I wroth and ſmote him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſinne, nor puniſhment of ſinne, can by mony be ſatisfyed before God, Chriſt hath ſatisfyed him for us, and is come into the World to call ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>As for purgeing of the ſoules after this life, of the remnant of the filthineſſe, whereof they had no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor meanes, to cleanſe themſelves in this life, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the new Doctrine of the Church of Roome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to finiſh, and to purge themſelves in Purgatory, I eſteeme it as Fables; as well all thoſe things which they write in their bookes, the Flower of Examples, the Goulden Legend, where there are ſuch pretty Hiſtoryes, as would talke any one aſleepe; and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand tales that are as fooliſh as falſe. And all this to the great diſhonour of God, overthroweing directly his Iuſtice and Mercy; His Iuſtice, for ſince there was
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20876:30"/>
ſatisfaction made for our ſinnes by Ieſus Chriſt, who hath taken upon him our infirmityes, and hath borne the puniſhment to purchaſe peace unto us, he cannot be unjuſt, for to aſke a ſecond ſatisfaction of us: unto which I adde that no puniſhment can be ſatisfactory in behalfe of ſinfull man, but eternall death: to ſay that the paines of Purgatory, and that imagined fire, is not for ſatisfaction, but for purgeing, it is to denye the words of the Apoſtle, who aſſureth us on Gods part, that the blood of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, hath cleanſed us from all our ſinnes. It is alſo againſt his Mercy, for if he pardoneth, he quitteth the debt, and forgiveth the puniſhment. To impute unto him then to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, is to robbe him of his Mercy, for to puniſh is proper to Iuſtice; and to pardon to mercy. Surely that Child would thinke his Father had deceaved him, if, after he had given him aſſurance of the Pardon of his fault, he cauſed him to be whipt to the blood:</p>
            <p>Now, ſince the greatneſſe and the durance of the paines of that imaginary fire and place, are eſteemed equall to thoſe of Hell, ſuch as the damned ſuffer, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting that they are not eternall, yet notwithſtanding of a long durance, every mortall ſinne requireing 7 yeares to be diſſolved in that fire, and well evaporated; now to give ſome comfort to ſuch as muſt paſſe this refineing place, before they can enter into Paradiſe, they have found a way to touch the tongue of thoſe that are in theſe flames with a drop of water, which are the indulgences graunted by the Pope, unto thoſe that ſhall merit it by giveing monyes to all thoſe chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20876:31"/>
in which they ſhall ſolemniſe the Pompes, that are ordained on the dayes of Iubily, or other times, on which they ſhall be diſtributed, according to the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the treaſure of the Church, which is rich in the merits of the Church, and ſuch good works which thoſe have done, that have payed more then they ought: That is it that can be purchaſed by thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſoules, which goe in pilgrimage to our Lady of Loretta, S. Iames in Galice, but eſpecially to Roane, <note n="†" place="margin">Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of the Coard of S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, by Pope Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus the fifth, 1585</note> where in three months of the yeare, the Brothers &amp; Siſters, that have girded themſelves with the Coard of S. Francis, may gaine, foure million eight hundred ſixty three thouſand two hundred and ſeven and fifty yeares Indulgence, beſides the forty dayes, <hi>to increaſe the ſervice of God, to the honour and reverence of Saint Francis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe are the words of the Bull, ſo that the ſervice of God be for S. Francis. How much could one gain then in a yeare, and how much in ten yeare? For this ſpring never dryeth, provided that the purſe never be empty. And doubt not, but all other Orders have alſo their priviledges, and gratifications, in ſo farre, that thoſe which beleeve theſe things, have reaſon to cry out with admiration, to the praiſe of the liberty of the Pope, in the diſtribution of ſo many indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, O the depth of riches and Indulgences of the Pope;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18, 19.</note> but thoſe that beleeve the contrary, <hi>and know, that they were not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſilver and gould, from their vaine converſation, but with the precious blood of Christ, as of a Lambe without blemiſh and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20876:31"/>
without ſpot,</hi> ſay, that life everlaſting is a gift of God, and thoſe that can purchaſe it with mony, are worthy to be ſpoken to, as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to Simon Magus: <hi>Thy mony periſh with thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou hast thought, that the gift of God may be purchaſed with Monye; Thou haſt neyther part nor Lot in this matter, for thy heart is not right in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnto theſe indulgences are faſtned the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Saints, by whoſe merits they pretend to obtaine a great part in Paradiſe, and theſe Saints ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for their miracles, which they have done dure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their life here, or after their death, paralelled by thoſe of the Prophets, and of our Saviour Chriſt, ſhall be found much inferiour and baſer. Among theſe are not forgotten the Reliques, which are under the Tables of the Altars, which are ſeen through a glaſſe, thoſe which you muſt beleeve without ſeeing, ſo many armes and heads of one body, of which every one gloryeth to have the true, one a certaine witneſſe, that neyther the one nor the other have the truth. And though, after the Goſpell beganne to be more fully manifeſted, then in the times of our forefathers, yet they have a few yeares agoe brought out of the grave divers new bones, to increaſe Idolatry, for the credit of ſuch as were never knowne heretofore: which ſerved mightily to the advancement of Ignatius de Loyola, to make him aſcend out of the Lower rancke of the <hi>Bleſsed Fathers,</hi> unto a Higher of <hi>Saints,</hi> by a tricke of a Canon of the Pope;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20876:32"/>
For when that Miracle was done (if it be true) the Pope had not yet drawn him out of that Bleſſedneſſe, to take place amongſt the Saincts. The narration is witneſſed by Iames Blaſe, Biſhop of S. Omer, ſigned with his hand, and ſealed with his ſeale, that, in the towne of Bourbourg, a Diocy under his Biſhoprick, the 15. of Iuly, 1610. there was a mayde, which was brought to the utmoſt of her life, by retention of her Vrine, the ſpace of 26 dayes, was cured as ſoone as the Reliques of Loyola (without ſpecifieing what member) had touched the party affected, the water takeing his ordinary courſe without paine. This mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous worke was printed at Luyck, by Leonard Streel; at Paris by Pater du Croc; and at Roan by Adrian Ouyn, in the ſame yeare 1610. In other places other ſuch miracles were done; and at leaſt the poore blinde people beleeve them; and becauſe they are printed, they print them alſo into their own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that aſke miracles teſtify that they are infidels, for the beleeving need no miracles,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 22. Tonges are for a ſigne, not to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, but to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve not.</note> but thoſe that beleeve not, as in the 1 Ioh. 4.1. <hi>Beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whether they are of God:</hi> So muſt one not beleeve every Miracle, but try the Miracle whether it be of God. And behould the marke given to the people of Iſrael by the Almighty himſelf: <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet or a dreamer of dreames, and giveth thee a ſigne or a wonder, and the ſigne or the wonder come to paſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13, 1, 2, 3, 5.</note> 
               <hi>whereof he ſpake vnto thee, ſaying: let us goe after other Gods, which thou haſt not knowne, and let us ſerve
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20876:32"/>
them; Thou ſhalt not hearken vnto the words of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or that dreamer of dreames, for the Lord your God prooveth you, to know whether you love the Lord your God with all your ſoule: And that Prophet or that dreamer of dreames ſhall be put to death, becauſe he hath ſpoken to turne you away from the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſeeth not that the miracles, whether true or falſe, which are taught in the Church of Rome, doe tend to turne the Chriſtian people from the adoration of the true God to that of the Creatures? Therefore ought one to caſt them away, for <hi>they teach but lyes;</hi> as it is alſo written of the Images:<note place="margin">Ier. 10, 15.</note> 
               <hi>They are vanity and the workes of errour.</hi> How happy then are they to whom God giveth grace to know this abuſe, and forſake it with all their heart!</p>
            <p>And as for Reliques, the H. Scripture doth recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend none to us, but to the contrary ſheweth us, to prevent ſuch Idolatryes, as we ſee to be ſo riſe in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; God himſelfe would hide ſo ſure the body of Moſes, who had done ſuch ſervice unto the people, that unto this preſent day his grave is yet unknowne: For it is probable that the Children of Iſrael would quickly have fallen to Idolatry, ſince they did hang after the Idols and falſe Gods of the Gentiles. The Example of that good King Hezechias is worth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, in that <hi>he did take away the high places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 18, 4.</note> 
               <hi>and brake the Images, and cutt downe the groves, and brake in pieces the braſen Serpent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Moſes had made; For vnto thoſe dayes the Children of Iſrael did burne incenſe to it.</hi> For if there were ever any thing worthy to be kept
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20876:33"/>
for a relique, it was that that deſerved it, for that <note n="†" place="margin">Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 21, 9</note> Serpent was commanded by God, and being looked upon according to his commandement, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe adjoyned unto it, the perſons that were bitten by the fiery Serpents, were healed. Behould a great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, yet notwithſtanding, becauſe it was an object, and occaſion of Idolatry, it was broken in peeces by King Hezekiah; And ſince the Scripture hath not commanded us to keep the forſkin of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, or his garment or teares, the milke of the Virgin Mary, her hayre, or ſmock, the Stoole of S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a thouſand ſuch fopperyes, which they ſhew for reliques, and to which they pray in the Church of Rome: By what authority doe they obtrude theſe to the people? All theſe thinges are as truely amongſt them,<note place="margin">Act. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>as the Cough of S. Ioſeph, and the ſhadowe of S. Peter.</hi> By this appeareth plainly, that the world deſires to be deceaved.</p>
            <p>I will not ſpeake of the holy Beads, Agnus Dei, made of wax, unto which they attribute the ſame ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that they doe unto the blood of Chriſt; Of the Maſſes, for the dead, and the prayers ſayd over them: cleane contrary to that which they ſay of the eſtate of the ſoules in<note n="‡" place="margin">In the Canon of the Maſſe they ſay, that they ſleep the ſleep of peace, but the peines of purgatory fire, are very contrary to ſleep. They pray alſo for thoſe that reſt in Chriſt, then alſo for our Lady and the Saints.</note> purgatory. I ſpeake not of the hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bells, at the melting whereof, whileſt the mettall runneth into the mould, they ſing: <hi>Veni Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Spiritus,</hi> &amp;c. and call upon the Holy Ghoſt, for the good Succeſſe whereof; When the Bells are caſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20876:33"/>
they ſing: <hi>Te Deum Laudamus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We praiſe thee O Lord;</hi> At the laſt, <hi>a Domino factum est iſtud: This the Lord hath done.</hi> When they hang them up, they ſprinkell them with holy water, ſacred Oyle, &amp; bleſſed ſalt, with prayers, that the Bels <hi>be filled with the vertue of the Holy Ghoſt, for to bring people to devotion, to drive away Devills, aſswage Tempeſts, &amp;c.</hi> Afterward, they are ſeven times toucht with the Vnction, on the outſide; then perfumed with incenſe and Mirrhe, with prayers, <hi>that they may be filled with the deawe of the H. Spirit.</hi> Finally, after all, wetted with holy Water, the Prieſt (the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers, laying hands upon them) giveth them their names; the Bells being covered with foure yards of Linnen, as many Ceremonies, as in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; and to all actions, ſeverall invocations of the name of God: which all are impious and prophane. They take the ſame courſe with the ſhippes: I paſſe over the ſacriledge, ſo frequent in the Church of Rome, to ſay ſilent Maſſes, for Horſes, Hogges, &amp; other Beaſts, for which Chriſt did not ſhed his blood: they call theſe Maſſes by the name of thoſe Saints, to whom they attribute the eſpeciall care of thoſe brute beaſtes, as S. Eloy for the Horſes, S. Anthony for the Hogges: I mention not the impiety of certaine Prieſts, that uſe the Sacrament in conjurations and ſorceries, and of thoſe that make the toades eat their conſecrated Hoſt, as may be proved by the judgement paſſed not many yeares ſince, in the Parliament of Provence,<note place="margin">Lavac. conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, cap. 6, p. 24. b.</note> over Prieſt Gaufredi, a renowned Conjurer: For I know that thoſe ſinnes, though practiſed in their Religion, are
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20876:34"/>
not approve of; ſo alſo though I condemne the bad manners of many amongſt them, that was not the principall motive that occaſioned me to come away, (for every where are to be found bad and good) but the Doctrine which they teach there, contrary to the truth of the Goſpell. There are alſo other points e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, beſides thoſe here formerly obſerved, but I thinke theſe to ſuffiſe; to ſhew that God haveing given me this knowledge. I was obliged to advance my ſelfe by it, and to give him thankes, that he hath not onely inſtructed me, but alſo ſtrengthened my heart with a holy reſolution, to come away (as I did) from the profeſſion of the Romiſh Church, and following the inward motion of the ſpirit of God, without being induced or inticed by any perſon, but urged by my conſcience, I joyne my ſelfe to the profeſſion of the truth of the Goſpell, as it is taught in the Reformed Churches, by the word of God, which acknowledge Ieſus Chriſt alone for their head, of which they are the true ſpouſe, and which alone deſerves the title of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Apoſtolick Church; into the boſome whereof I yeeld my ſelf, to be there nouriſhed by the ſincere worde of God, which is the milke of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and comforted and ſtrengthened by the uſe of the Sacraments, which are there adminiſtred, according to his ordinance; Praying God to ſhew me that mercy, that I may live and dye in that profeſſion craveing pardon from him, for the love of his holy Sonne, that have ſo long participated with ſo many Idolatries, Superſtition and abominations: deſireing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20876:34"/>
the true faithfull of the Church, to acknowledge me in this Chriſtian profeſſion, and to love me as one of the members of the body of Chriſt, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Saints. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letters">
            <head>
               <hi>LETTERS</hi> Written from Bruſsels, to Don EMAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL, Son of my Lord the Prince of Portugall, ſince his comeing over into the Vnited Provinces of the Netherlands.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>De ſon Alteſſe Sereniſſime, en Eſpagnol.</head>
                  <p>LOs negocios corryentes importa mucho que os legueis a qui a Bruſſelas encubierto, dexando ay toda vuestra gente; aſsi os lo pido, y qui me abiſareys en llegardo, pues ymporta mucho. Y Dios os guarde como deſseo. De Bruſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, eu 11. de Hebrero, 1633.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ISABEL:</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>In Engliſh.</head>
                  <p>IT is neceſſary for preſent affaires, that you come hither to Bruſſells privately, leaveing there all your folkes. This it is that I deſire you ſhould doe, and that you advertiſe me of your arrivall, for much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon it. God keep you in his protection, as I hope. From Bruſſells the eleventh of February, 1633.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>ISABELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20876:35"/>
                  <head>From my Lord the Prince of Portugall.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SONNE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>The death of her Highneſſe hath caſt us all into great heavineſſe, the Children in ſuch a cauſe ſerve to comfort their Fathers: Therefore I pray you to take your journy hither, as ſoone as you can; and I wiſh you could perſwade your Siſter <hi>Donna Louiſa,</hi> to take a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe this way with you, for as little a while as ſhee pleaſeth. You may counſell her, &amp;c. Tell her the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſecurity there is here. You are obliged to doe it for your honours ſake, and for Gods ſake above all. The advice of good Freinds ſhall be a great help unto you. The Lord ſuggeſt a holy Counſell unto you, full of his grace, and beleeve that I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Father <hi>D. EMANVEL.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Bruſsells, on S. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas-day,</hi>
                        <date>1633.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:20876:35"/>
                  <head>De Frere Elias de S. Marie Magdalaine. <hi>Iheſus Marie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>PAx Chriſti. Dios quede con V. R. y noz de gracia para ne perder lo que eternamente dura, par lo que tan brevemente paſſa lo que mucho ſe deve conſidera, por mui cierto tengo, que a todo tiempo que V.R. quiſiere continuar la vida que con tanta perfecion ha començado, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos le reciberemos en los braſos, porque aſsi lo merece la buena compagnia que nos hizó. Dizen que V.R. muda de Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; para ſalvarſe muy ſegura es la Catholica. V.R. lo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidere, porque errar en ecte punto, ſera errar eternamente. Io ſere hasta la muerte, muy, verdadero amigo y ſervidor de V. R. y comotal, me alegrare de ſus bienes, y ſentire ſus males, de que Dios guarde a V.R. como yo lo deſeo, y le de lus para que<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>vea lo mucho que pierde, en perdera a Dios que en los manos ſe le puſo.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>De V.R. Humilde ſiervo fray</hi> Elias de S. Maria Magdalaine.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>En 15. de Enero</hi> 1634.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>Jn Engliſh.</head>
                  <p>THe Peace of Chriſt. God be with you, and give us his grace, not to looſe that which is eternall, to poſſeſſe that which paſſeth away ſuddenly, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth a good conſideration. I am verily aſſured, that at what time ſoever you ſhall pleaſe to proſecute
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20876:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Religion, which you have begunne with ſuch perfection, we all ſhould receave you with open arms: For ſuch deſerveth the good fellowſhip we had of you. The ſpeech is that you change in Religion, conſider well, that the Catholick Church is full of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſalvation, and to faile in this point is to looſe himſelfe eternally. I ſhall remaine till death your truſty freind and ſervant, and as ſuch a one I ſhall rejoyce in your proſperity, and Symphatize with your afflictions, from which I pray God to preſerve you, and that he would open your eyes, that you may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how much you looſe, in looſing God, whom you have had in your hands.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your humble Servant and Brother</hi> Elias of S. Mary Madelaine.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>15. Ianuary, 1634.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
